<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The second part of the new survey of the Turkish empire, containing I.  The extent of its dominion, when, how and by whom conquered.  II.  An account of the Tartars.  III.  The life of Mahomet the Imposter.  IV.  Their militia.  V.  Their government civil and ecclesiastick.  VI.  The continuation of their history.  Being now and absolute and compleat discovery of what is worth knowledge, or is any way satisfactory to curiosity, in that mighty nation.</title>
            <author>Marsh, Henry, fl. 1663-1664.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 183KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 94 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B43403</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">297426964</idno>
  <idno type="VID">208142</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240856449</idno>
  
            <idno type="OCLC"> 297426964</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocn 297426964</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M732A</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B43403)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 208142)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2923:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The second part of the new survey of the Turkish empire, containing I.  The extent of its dominion, when, how and by whom conquered.  II.  An account of the Tartars.  III.  The life of Mahomet the Imposter.  IV.  Their militia.  V.  Their government civil and ecclesiastick.  VI.  The continuation of their history.  Being now and absolute and compleat discovery of what is worth knowledge, or is any way satisfactory to curiosity, in that mighty nation.</title>
                  <author>Marsh, Henry, fl. 1663-1664.</author>
                  <author>Chantry, John, d. 1662?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 172, [2] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J. Best for Henry Marsh at the Princes Arms in Chancery Lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1664.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Epistle dedicatory signed: Henry Marsh.  Cf.  Wing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Allegorical frontispiece labelled "Mahomets tombe" signed: I. Chantry, scu[--].</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: lacks postscript.  Postscript  is supplied in manuscript.  Imprint  reads for J. Best for Henry Marsh.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="geographic_name">Austro-Turkish War, 1661-1664 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Turkey --  History --  1453-1683 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Turkey --  History --  Mehmed IV, 1648-1687 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Maria Cecilia Caride </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Maria Cecilia Caride</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:208142:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:208142:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>
                     <hi>MAHOMETS TOMBE</hi> A the Grand Signior B the Crim Tartar C the Emperour of Ger: D the Pope: I: Chantry. seu<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:208142:2"/>
            <p>THE SECOND PART OF THE New Survey OF THE <hi>TƲRKISH EMPIRE,</hi> Containing
<list>
                  <item>I. <hi>The Extent of its Dominion, when, how, and by whom conquered.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>II. <hi>An Account of the</hi> Tartars.</item>
                  <item>III. <hi>The Life of</hi> Mahomet the <hi>Impostor.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>IV. <hi>Their Militia.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>V. <hi>Their Government Civil and Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siastick.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>VI. <hi>The Continuation of their History.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Being now an Absolute and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat Discovery of what is worth Knowledge, or is any way satisfactory to Curiosity, in that Mighty Nation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. Best</hi> for <hi>Henry Marsh</hi> at the Princes Arms in <hi>Chancery-lane.</hi> 1664.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:208142:3"/>
            <p>Imprimatur.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>VVill. Morice.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Jan. 9. 1663.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:208142:3"/>
            <head>To the Right Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>Thomas</hi> Lord <hi>Arundel</hi> of <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour,</hi> and Count of the sacred Empire.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it please your Lordship,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is due to the glory of your Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lustrious Family a more ample and sufficient Discourse of the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject
<pb facs="tcp:208142:4"/> I have resumed, and I must therefore humbly crave your pardon, that I presume to confine the extended re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nown of your Name through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Turkish Empire, to this abridgement of its Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness.</p>
            <p>Your valorous and victori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Ancestor left the Impres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of English Courage and Honour indelibly visible on the walls of <hi>Strigonium,</hi> which Town his noble atchieve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment did in effect restore to to the German <hi>Caesar,</hi> whose sentiments of so great a ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice have not onely worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ranked you (by successi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) with the most Noble Counts of the most sacred Empire, but signalized that merit with an English Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,
<pb facs="tcp:208142:4"/> conferred as a further reward thereof by our late Soveraign King <hi>James</hi> of bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed memory.</p>
            <p>Be your Lordship favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly pleased to permit there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore your Titles to be inscri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed to this Treatise, as by the matter thereof you have been entituled, to your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, and that with more splendid Remarques then the greatest Dignities in <hi>Europe</hi> can pretend to. And I no way doubt but that your great Name will prove as benign and propitious to this design as it hath been disastrous and formidable to the Turks.</p>
            <p>Wishing your Lordship all Prosperity, answerable to
<pb facs="tcp:208142:5"/> your own particular Vertue, which hath been no less sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally famous in the late Royal Service, I humbly beg leave to subscribe my self</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
               <signed>Your most humble and obedient Servant, Henry Marsh.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:208142:5"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving lately publish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the First Part of a <hi>New Survey of Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ky,</hi> when for Expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by reason such a Treatise was every day expected; I could not possibly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gest all that concerns so spacious and mighty an Empire into so small a Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume; I have now by the favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble encouragement of the formers ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation perfected and compleated the Discourse, which I presume and doubt not will give ample satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the most curious and inquisitive Reader. There were some things in the former only mentioned, some things misrepresented, some things wholly o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted; but the perusal of this will rectifie all, whereby the equal Reader
<pb facs="tcp:208142:6"/> will perceive that it was not ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry nor common labour to contrive the Essentials of so great a State, so much distant from our knowledge, to every easie apprehension, and yet to have kept a decent reverence and respect to its Greatness.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="notice">
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>Because of a vulgar and most ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious error concerning <hi>Mahomets</hi> Tomb, it is prefixed in the peice be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Title, that it may be percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, it is not suspended by vertue of a Loadstone in the Roof of the Temple, but is placed by the side thereof as Monuments with us usually are; As Dr. <hi>Heylin,</hi> Mr. <hi>Sandys,</hi> Sir <hi>Henry Blunt,</hi> Sir <hi>Walter Raleigh,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers do agree.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 21. Line 20. for 1642. read 1462. page 54. the mention of the Isle of <hi>Rhodes</hi> ought to be referred to page 97.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:208142:6"/>
            <head>THE SECOND PART OF THE NEW SURVEY OF THE Turkish Empire.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> The Extent and Dominion of this Empire.</head>
               <p>
                  <label>The Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face.</label>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Ʋrky</hi> owes so much to its barbarous power and greatness that it is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most bankrupt in its re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nown and glory, while the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian world debar'd of any free and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:208142:7"/> unjealousied converse, or wanting the advantage thereof by the rudeness, ignorance, and vast de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>populations of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>espective Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces of this spacious Monarchy do conclude and gaze upon it as a Monster, spreading and winding his pernicious bulk upon the face of <hi>Europe,</hi> more by a brute impulse and sudden violent effort, then by the conduct and directions of true reason and policy, which by a just and exact disquisition of their atcheivements and conquests,<label>Our Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Turkish Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</label> will be found of the best extraction from the truest refined wisdom, and to relish of that pure and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuine intellect, which in the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born world is reported and credited to have descended upon, and blest this Tract and Regions, however our vicious and depraved sense, perplexed with the Matchivilian In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigues of Government, doth falsly conceive of it as exotick simplicity, and of their Prowess as the forced result of their Savage
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:208142:7"/> and ferally Rapinous dispositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p>Our purpose therefore is in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribing of the dimensions of this large and ample Territory, to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve the manner and means of their augmentation, and Coalition into this entire and grand consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stency, with a Chronology of each Provinces reduction to the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Scepter from under the Government of their former and natural Princes. The present Politiques, and Civil and Ecclesi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>astical, Martial and Judiciary Administration of this Potent and most extensive Soverainty, its Magnificence, Pomp and Splen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor, not interfering with what hath been said before, but in a distinct and orderly method, for perfect and plenary information of the Reader.</p>
               <p>Nor will it therefore be necessary to pry into those lurking holes and abdite retreats of their despicable and unobserved Ancestry, since
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:208142:8"/> the disparagement of their Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals is rather the glory of their adult and mature estate and gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deur, and concerns not their story or present condition, besides that it hath already been briefly, but satisfactorily mentioned in the former part.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>enient <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>cite of <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>he Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ire.</label>Considering this Dominion in general, there is nothing can be faulted in it which is requisite to the support of its grandeur. For its Scituation it is placed most con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniently for an universal or fifth Monarchy, being devided equally into <hi>Europe</hi> and <hi>Asia,</hi> the very Center of the Earth, whereby he may be ready on all occasions to stretch his Conquest either way, and be quick and ready at hand with recruits and supplies to carry on a war in either quarter. His Imperial City of <hi>Constantinople</hi> being the extremest limit of both Regions, officiously attended and served by two Seas, the Euxine and the Mediterranean, which combine
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:208142:8"/> their waters by the walls of the Magnificent <hi>Seraglia,</hi> and do joyn in Homage to this mighty Lord and Ruler.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>His con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant po<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy in m<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>king wa<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </label>He hath also large Territories in <hi>Affrick,</hi> and the Red Sea under his command in part, so that of the habitable world he hath the biggest and fairest proportion, and by that means may when his Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition shall incite him extend his Arms and Dominions further, in any of these quarters, provided the Conquest be worth the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chase, and his affairs at Home or the opposite Regions will afford him opportunity, for it is to be noted the Grand Signior never makes War in two places together, nor long in one place, either fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the contagions of his Enemies manners should spread among his own people, which he carefully avoids, as the bane of his Tyranny, or else suspecting that his own deficiencies in the Art Military, or some other inconveniencies of his
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:208142:9"/> Souldiery may be notified to the Adversary by any continuance in their Country, just like a Lyon and a Dragon fighting by insults or results, taking and leaving as he pleaseth, so that most of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign and force seems to lye in the invasion and intrusive manage thereof; The French fury, and Turkish incursion being equally terrible and as as soon abated, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less extraordinary Fortune and other concurrent advantages hold them longer in breath and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secution, which is much to be feared in this present juncture, and the condition of <hi>Hungary,</hi> from whence and the <hi>Europaean</hi> parts adjacent we will begin this Survey of this mighty Empire.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>clavonia <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>escribed.</label>We will enter into that part which is nearest to us, and leads in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the body of his Dominions, <hi>Scla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vonia,</hi> divided now into six Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, bounded on the East with <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>via, Macedonia</hi> and <hi>Epirus,</hi> from which they are parted by the river
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:208142:9"/>
                  <hi>Drinus,</hi> and a line drawn from thence unto the <hi>Adriatick;</hi> on the West with <hi>Carniola</hi> in <hi>Germany</hi> and <hi>Histria</hi> in the Seigniory of <hi>Venice,</hi> from which last they are divided by the River <hi>Arsia;</hi> on the North with <hi>Hungary;</hi> and on the South the <hi>Adriatick</hi> Sea, containing in length eight hundred <hi>Italian</hi> miles, (the breadth being 325) those Provinces are, <hi>Windisland, Croatia, Bosnia, Dalmatia, Libur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia</hi> or the County of <hi>Zara,</hi> and <hi>Sclav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nian</hi> Isles.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Bosnia</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed.</label>Of this Territory <hi>Bosnia</hi> is wholly the <hi>Turks,</hi> it was united as a Kingdom unto <hi>Hungary,</hi> and under the Homage thereof a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom by it self in 1420, as is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported; but as it was a Kingdom of a latter date, so was it of as short continuance, for in the year 1464. <hi>Mahomet</hi> the Great having taken <hi>Constantinople,</hi> and almost all the rest of <hi>Greece,</hi> suddenly surprised and seized it, together with <hi>Stephen</hi> the last King there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:208142:10"/> he most barbarously command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him to be flead alive (whereby he terrified all other Pretenders) and then converted it to a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince of his Empire; thereafter, and yet governed by one of the principallest of his Bashaws.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>DALMATIA;</hi> In this Province, though the <hi>Venetians</hi> have a share, yet it is a very inconsiderable one, yet it stretches all North along the <hi>Adriatick</hi> Sea or Gulf of <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice,</hi> (whereto they pretend a sole dominion and Jurisdiction) for they pay for the customs of all trade and merchandize, a certain stipend yearly to the <hi>Turk,</hi> with which engine it is thought they have for so many ages held play with him being ever in danger of a rup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and war, but much against their wills and inclinations;<label>The <hi>Gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nd <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>eignior</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>rotector <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>f the <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>tate of <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>agusa.</hi>
                  </label> upon the same account the <hi>Great Turk</hi> is Protector of the little Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth of <hi>Ragusa,</hi> very rich for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly by their Traffick upon the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:208142:10"/> adjoyning Sea; without this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection they had long ere now fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len into the hands of the <hi>Veneti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> as on the other side they are preserved by the State of <hi>Venice</hi> from being a prey to their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector. So that it is the very paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel of the State of <hi>Geneva</hi> lying betwixt the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Spaniard.</hi> This <hi>Ragu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sa,</hi> is the Maritime descent into <hi>Turkie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Bosnia</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed.</label>The ISLES (some of which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to <hi>Ragusa</hi>) as <hi>Curzola</hi> or <hi>Corcyra,</hi>X <hi>Zara</hi> and the rest have been often ransacked and pillaged by the Turks, but never posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed by them, as not caring for such remote and dangerous Tenures, being placed in a boysterous and destructive Sea.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>County of <hi>Zara.</hi>
                  </label>In the County of ZARA the <hi>Turk</hi> hath a good part, as he hath firm footing in <hi>Windischland,</hi> the parts whereof lying much to <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary</hi> on the North and East, do groan under the Bondage of the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:208142:11"/>
                  <hi>Turkish Garrisons,</hi> some whereof are also placed in <hi>Croatia,</hi> where the <hi>Turk</hi> in 1592. took <hi>Whitiz</hi> the Metropolis, though fortified strongly both by Art and Nature in the form of an sland by the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Ʋna,</hi> when contrary to the Articles of surrender, he put all the Souldiers immediately to the sword. Now for better elucidati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Turks</hi> part in the whole we will sum it up in this partiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The whole apportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</label>The <hi>Venetians</hi> possess the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est part of the Islands, and all the Sea coasts from the River <hi>Arisia</hi> to the Bay of <hi>Cattharo</hi> (the City and Commonwealth of <hi>Ragusa</hi> only excepted; the House of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stria,</hi> as Kings of <hi>Hungary,</hi> the Inland parts of <hi>Windischland</hi> and <hi>Croatia;</hi> and the <hi>Turks</hi> who set footing herein the reign of Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met the Great, the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Bosnia,</hi> the patronage of <hi>Ragusia,</hi> some Towns in <hi>Windisch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>atia,</hi> and all the resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:208142:11"/> of <hi>Dalmatia,</hi> from the Bay of <hi>Cattaro</hi> to <hi>Albania,</hi> so that he hath the better half of this Region of <hi>Sclavonia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Hungary:</label>In <hi>HƲNGARY</hi> it self, by the Victories of <hi>Solyman</hi> the Magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, who (upon the death of <hi>Lewis</hi> the Second, King of <hi>Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> that lost unfortunately the Battel of <hi>Mohatz,</hi> and was drowned in his flight) was called in by <hi>John Sepusio Vayvod</hi> of <hi>Transilva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi> chosen King by election of the States of <hi>Hungary,</hi> against the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditary claim of <hi>Ferdinand</hi> Arch Duke of <hi>Astria, &amp;c.</hi> such advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage was made in the dissention be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the two rival Kings, that upon the death of <hi>John Sepusio</hi> in 1540. that under color of Patronage to <hi>Stephen Johns</hi> Orphan whom he took into his own tuition, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards deprived (having delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated to put him to death) he seized <hi>Buda</hi> the Capital City, with other Towns, and from that time his
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:208142:12"/> successors, but especially himself, have never omitted any occasions or advantages of the Christian quarrels to enlarge their domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in this Kingdom, which same design this successeful present Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror hath so far prosecuted, that there remains not to the Emperor above four places of Note and strength in that Kingdom, which are <hi>Raab, Comorra, Toskay</hi> and <hi>Presburgh,</hi> the last confining upon <hi>Austria</hi> it self, while the whole Country, Towns and Villages, even beyond the limits of that Realm are subjected to, and lye open to this barbarous enemy.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition thereof.</label>So that most men conclude, <hi>Actum est de Hungaria,</hi> and give it over as a Province of the Turkish Empire, to which it was in as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward a condition after the battel of <hi>Keresture</hi> in 1578. when <hi>Mahomet</hi> the third took in <hi>Agria,</hi> and making advantage of the <hi>Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran</hi> innovation in <hi>Germany,</hi> which then divided the Princes thereof,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:208142:12"/>
                  <label>Battel of <hi>Keresture</hi>
                  </label> had swallowed the Conquest, but was so near an utter overthrow himself, being forced to forsake the field in a most disorderly frightful fight, in which with hast he lost his Turbant, that had not the Christians out of greediness of Plunder and Spoil, left the pursuit scarce begun, to rifle the Camp, which gave the Turks time and courage to rally again, <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met</hi> had hardly recovered <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantinople:</hi> But by reason of this disastrous covetousness the fortune of the battel was quite changed, with such a diversity, that as Dr. <hi>Heylin</hi> elegantly observeth, the <hi>Conquerours were beaten out of the field, and the vanquished ran away with the victory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Belgrade.</label>Among other possessions of the Turks in <hi>Hungary,</hi> before we depart thence, <hi>Belgrade</hi> anciently called <hi>Taurunum,</hi> or <hi>Alba Greca,</hi> once the possession of the Despots of <hi>Servia,</hi> by whom it was consigned to <hi>Sigismond</hi> King of <hi>Hungary,</hi> as
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:208142:13"/> the best able to maintain it, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serves our observation: it is seated upon the confluence of the <hi>Savus</hi> and <hi>Danow,</hi> by the former of which it is hemmed in on the <hi>North</hi> and on the <hi>East</hi> by the latter, it was heretofore the great Bulwark of <hi>Christendom</hi> against the Turks, who were often times worsted and defeated before it (especially <hi>Amu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rath</hi> the Second and <hi>Mahomet</hi> the Great) but at last taken to the shame of Christendom for not succouring the beseiged in time, by <hi>Solyman</hi> the Magnificent in the year 1552. not to mention some other principal places besides these named, as <hi>Gran</hi> or <hi>Strigonium,</hi> at the taking whereof by the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror <hi>Rodolph,</hi> in the year 1595. <label>
                     <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Arun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>el <hi>of</hi> Wardour.</label> Sir <hi>Thomas Arundel</hi> of <hi>Wardour</hi> for forcing the water Tower, and bringing thence a Turkish Banner, was made a Count of the Empire, and after Lord <hi>Wardour</hi> of <hi>Arundel</hi> by King <hi>James, Alba Regalis, Quinque Ecclesio, Zigeth, Temes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>war,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:208142:13"/> Pest Colocza</hi> an Arch-bishops see, &amp;c. and now <hi>Newhausel</hi> and <hi>Novigrad.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Dacia.</label>In <hi>DACIA,</hi> the Eastern bound of <hi>Hungary,</hi> he is absolute Lord and Master. In this Region are contained the Provinces of <hi>Transyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vania, Moldavia, Valachia, Rascia, Servia</hi> and <hi>Bulgaria,</hi> the four first in old <hi>Ducia</hi> North of the <hi>Danow,</hi> the two last in the new on the South side thereof.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Transilva<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nia.</label>
                  <hi>Transylvania</hi> bounded on the East with <hi>Moldavia,</hi> on the West with <hi>Ʋpper Hungary,</hi> on the North with <hi>Russia Nigra,</hi> on the South with <hi>Rascia</hi> and <hi>Valachia,</hi> hath its name from the great Woods lying between it and <hi>Hungary.</hi> This peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple is divided into seven Cantons, keeping their own laws, fatally and insensibly betrayed to the Turkish yoak, by <hi>John Sepusio</hi> the Son of <hi>Stephen,</hi> Vayvod of <hi>Transilvania</hi> (which was the title in use before <hi>Sigismund Battori,</hi> who stiled him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:208142:14"/> Prince) who as aforesaid called in <hi>Solyman:</hi> his Infant Son <hi>Stephen</hi> was afterwards by him made Vay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vod of <hi>Transilvania,</hi> a fine recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence for his Fathers kindness for the Turk: since which time the Grand Signor clayms the Investi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Provinces hereof, and a yearly Tribute, besides their initiating Bribes and Presents: <label>The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>olt of <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>rans<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ia.</hi>
                  </label> many revolts have been attempted, but none so signal as first, that of <hi>Sigismond Battori,</hi> who defeated several Turkish Armies, and shook off the Turkish yoke with scorn and indignation, but his suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessors have been forced to accept of it again, and their Subjects con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to pay the Tribute, for which they enjoy their National Laws and Liberties of Religion. Secondly that of <hi>Ragotzi</hi> in 1659. and 1660. who was likewise very successeful against the forces of this present <hi>Sultan,</hi> but he being woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in his last conflict with them, was carried to <hi>Varadin,</hi> where he
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:208142:14"/> ended his life, much honoured and lamented by his Subjects. <label>
                     <hi>Ragotzi</hi> dieth.</label>
                  <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radin</hi> which is one of the strongest peices of this Country, but Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rison'd by <hi>Hungarians,</hi> was soon af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter taken by the Visier Bassa, and the prosecution of the war into <hi>Hungary</hi> from this Pique hence undertaken, as from a neer view of those troubles and dangers which threatened the Empire of <hi>Germany</hi> on the other side. The present Prince of this Country <hi>Michael Apaffi,</hi> is wholly at the Devotion of the Turk, and is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciprocally caressed by them, but how long the kindness will last, the <hi>German</hi> war will soon determine: the <hi>Transilvanians</hi> are most part of them <hi>Calvinists.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Moldavia</hi> described.</label>
                  <hi>MOLDAVIA</hi> is bounded on the <hi>East</hi> with the Sea, on the <hi>West</hi> with <hi>Transylvania,</hi> on the <hi>North</hi> with the River <hi>Niester</hi> and <hi>Podolia</hi> a part of <hi>Poland,</hi> and on the <hi>South</hi> with <hi>Walachia,</hi> it is a
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:208142:15"/> fruitful Country, but very thin of people, by reason of those depopulations made by <hi>Turks, Tartars,</hi> and <hi>Cossacks,</hi> never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theless it supplies <hi>Constantinople</hi> with five hundred Ships laden yearly wish provision for <hi>Constan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople,</hi> it is in diameter every way three hundred miles, they beleive with the Greek Church, and are tolerated therein like other Cristi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in the same condition. Their Vayvod is a Tributary and Benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciary of the Grand Seignior, and is placed and displaced as he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth, but he that gives most com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly now adays is honoured with the Dignity. The eminentest of their Princes substituted in this manner have been <hi>John</hi> the Vay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vod about 1570. who gave a terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble overthrow to the Turks assisted by <hi>Peter</hi> the Vayvod of <hi>Valachia,</hi> who had bought, and now fought for the possession of the Vayvod-ship, but was at last perfideously murthered by the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:208142:15"/> Turks 1574. <label>The vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts of the Molda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vians to recover their Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty.</label> when <hi>Moldavia</hi> sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to them, but was again wrested from them forcibly by <hi>Aaron</hi> the Vayvode, confederate with <hi>Sigismond</hi> Prince of <hi>Transilva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi> whom themselves had placed, who being also again devested, and betrayed by <hi>Roswan</hi> one of his disloyal and ambitious Subjects, <hi>Moldavid</hi> sheltred it self under to the tuition of the <hi>Polanders,</hi> who have since placed some Vay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vods, but to their perpetual loss and trouble, and then of <hi>Rodol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus</hi> the Emperor, but at last again it reverted to the Turk, who raged there in the year 1622. when young <hi>Osman</hi> was Emperour, since which time the Vayvods have lived with good correspondence with the Port, and now attend this expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the Grand Seignor into <hi>Germany;</hi> but though they are ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solute Vassals, yet is not their Country quite conquered, or so much as marched over or through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly traversed by those Infidels.</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:208142:16"/>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Valachia</hi> described.</label>
                  <hi>VALACHIA</hi> is the next Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, once one and the same with <hi>Moldaevia,</hi> but by a modern di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinction defined and divided from it by the name of <hi>Transalpina,</hi> a ridge of Mountains crossing both Countries; they follow the Greek Church, and obey the Patriarch of <hi>Constantinople,</hi> whom those Christian parts of the world ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge as supreme: but as their Neighbours are ignorant of all letters, and so the fitter for the Mahumetan Impositions.</p>
               <p>It is in length five hundred, in breadth a hundred and twenty miles, and very plentiful of all things, the Store-house with the other adjacent Provinces of penu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious <hi>Asia,</hi> and gives credit and reputation as it borrows its ferti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, to the River <hi>Ister,</hi> which in its confines, and by the confluence of other Rivers into the <hi>Danow,</hi> is here so called. The people hereof were governed by Vayvods
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:208142:16"/> of their own, till the Turks inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion made them seek for the King of <hi>Hungaries</hi> protection, to whose often and very great discomfitures they have been highly instrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, but with various fortune, from the time of <hi>Bajazet</hi> the first, who vanquished their Prince, and was himself caged by <hi>Tamberlane,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till this last age.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Mahomets</hi> Policy.</label> It afterwards was resigned into the several vicine Princes, as the necessity and occasion of war ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vised, still stubborn against the Turkish yoke, while the prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fortune thereof made all the Territory about them to undergoe it; yet with a great deal less of slavery then the rest; For <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met</hi> the great in the year 1642. very unsuccessfully undertaking the entire conquest of this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, wherein he found more Rocks, Mountains, and precipices then humane defence, prudently declining any further attempt, by the more destructive mines of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:208142:17"/> Empire, hurled the state thereof in to a Convulsive and distracted Ruine, by the intestine Divisions of the two Brothers, <hi>Wladus</hi> the Prince, and <hi>Dracula</hi> his younger brother, whose interest he set up and assisted to their common de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction.</p>
               <p>By which means and his Auxili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arys residence there. He was not to be disputed with longer, and thereupon was acknowledged the Lord of the Principality under certain limitations and restrictions to his supreme power, which the neerness of a continual ayd from the Christian world adjoyning thereunto induced him to allow. We have spoken of <hi>Michael</hi> the Noble Vayvod thereof in 1659. who had in all probobility by his singular valour and generosity freed this warlike Nation from their dependance on this Tyrant, and should mention the like bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of their late Vayvod in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction with <hi>Regotski,</hi> but the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:208142:17"/> urgent Fate of the Empire would not not have those petit struglings to bear any part in her general calamity; yea, hath suffered those puny and indifferent limbs of Christianity to be monstrously turned into Arms against her, and to assist the barbarous violences that now oppress and ravage the <hi>Austrian</hi> Dominions, <label>Moldavia a very ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pensive conquest.</label> yet have the Turks got nothing in this conquest but a safe Retreat, which hath cost them five times the money they will ever make of it, were it not that there assurances of our divisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons will one day quit their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence, as otherwise, which God for his mercy vouchsafe, it is now and may prove to be able to pay his score, if once he turns his back to the face of a competent and couragious Christian Army.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Rascia.</label>
                  <hi>RASCIA</hi> is bounded on the <hi>East</hi> with <hi>Valachia,</hi> on the <hi>West</hi> with <hi>Hungaria,</hi> on the <hi>North</hi> with <hi>Transilvania,</hi> on the <hi>South</hi> with
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:208142:18"/> the River <hi>Danow,</hi> and on the <hi>East</hi> divided from <hi>Valaohia,</hi> by the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Aluta.</hi> The people hereof are so wretched that they have lost their very name, not a Gentleman surviving this depression, they have been linked into the Government of their Neighbours, but now scarce know any body but their Tyrannical Masters, to whom they do excellent service, when this natural courage which like Brutes they retain, is emulously provoked by other more barbarous Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.<label>Unjust &amp; indiscreet ambition deserved<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</label> By their union with <hi>Servia</hi> they tasted of the same fortune, and were subjugated by the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Amurath</hi> the second, at the time that those <hi>Despots</hi> (who had unjustly vanquished this people) were captivated themselves. Fate shewing herein, how desperate a folly it is for Princes or (to descend to) private men, to undertake any unjust, though advantageous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign upon another, while there is a Superior Enemy thereby invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:208142:18"/> to the umpirage of the quarrel. These <hi>Rascians</hi> do yet so retain their primitive hatred against the Turks, that upon all occasions they have been ready to wreak themselves, but to very little pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, more then to show their more noble extract and ancestry.</p>
               <p>The three Provinces mentioned before <hi>Rascia,</hi> do and have enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed more liberty then any people under the Turkish Dominions, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause first the Turk hath not Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonies to plant them, being not so numerous as his Armys speak him for all his <hi>Polygamy,</hi> and secondly because their often overthrows (as they have infeebled their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, and in their long resistance desolated the Country, so that a man cannot find an Inn or Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in a days riding) have dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heartn'd an expedition on purpose, <hi>Mahomet</hi> the Great, who first at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted them, saying in great an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger that he came not to fight with Beasts, or which was more unequal
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:208142:19"/> against Nature it self, who had by so many abrupt or uncouth ways hindred the progress of his most industrious and eager Ambition, which his successors notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding from that kind of precarious Soverainty have improved into an awful submission, and address to the Port with two hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand Chequins yearly, which makes some 45. thousand pound sterling besides the Fees and Presents of the respective Princes. But what their condition is now like to be, the event of this present enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prise will best declare, but as now they are not fit for, or else not worth his fury, onely miserable <hi>Rascia,</hi> not honoured with a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour, suffers all extremity. And so we must pass the <hi>Danow</hi> to its Southern shore, the two King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, or despotical Provinces of <hi>SERVIA</hi> and <hi>BƲLGA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RIA.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Servia</hi> sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed.</label>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:208142:19"/>
                  <hi>SERVIA</hi> is bounded on the <hi>East</hi> with <hi>Bulgaria,</hi> on the <hi>West</hi> with <hi>Bosnia,</hi> on the <hi>North</hi> with the <hi>Danubius,</hi> on the <hi>South</hi> with <hi>Albania</hi> and part of <hi>Macedon,</hi> a rich and fruitful country for grain and gain, concealed in the reposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories of several mines of Gold and Silver, and therefore much peopled by the Turks after their general Excision and Massacre (in a manner) of the Christian Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants by <hi>Amurath</hi> in the year 1367. <label>Mahomet the great seizeth it.</label> when he took <hi>Nissa</hi> their Capital City, and Key of the Country, in revenge of their Despots assisting the <hi>Hungarians</hi> in the siege of <hi>Adrianople,</hi> but after the death of <hi>Lazarus</hi> the last Despot, <hi>Mahomet</hi> the Great not satisfied with a Tribute which <hi>Amurath</hi> had impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, dispossessed his three Orphans <hi>Peter, John,</hi> and <hi>Martyn</hi> (who fled to the <hi>Hungarian</hi> protection) in title of <hi>Lazarus</hi> s two other brothers who craved his assistance,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:208142:20"/> and thereby with dread and Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror destroyed most of the Natives, by empaling, gaunching, fleaing, and all other devices of Torture, so that he quickly tamed their cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, and made them the second province of the Eastern, or Greek Europe, that acknowledged and humbled it self to his Conquest and Dominion, in the year 1460.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Bulgaria</hi> discribed.</label>
                  <hi>BƲLGARIA</hi> is bounded on the East with the <hi>Euxine</hi> Sea, West with <hi>Servia,</hi> on the North with the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Danow,</hi> which is here called <hi>Ister,</hi> and on the South with <hi>Thrace.</hi> It was governed by Kings till <hi>Amu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rath</hi> the first reduced it by his Arms, (and the abject submission of <hi>Sas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menos</hi> the last Prince, who hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled himself in a winding sheet before that Tyrant in 1369.) after by <hi>Bajazet</hi> his Son, not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent therewith, made a Province under the absolute Government of the Turks; who in <hi>Nicopolis,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:208142:20"/> Sophia</hi> and <hi>Silistria</hi> have three San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jacks, or Major Generals under the command of the <hi>Beglerbeg,</hi> or Viceroy of <hi>Greece.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is a mountainous and woody Country, the Plains thereof being thick Planted with tall Tree, so that it furnisheth <hi>Constantinople</hi> with fewel, and is a good defence against any sudden irruptions into the more inward part of <hi>Romania;</hi> famous for the many Battels fought herein by <hi>Trajan</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror, who built <hi>Nicopolis,</hi> inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted <hi>The City of Victory,</hi> in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of his Conquest of <hi>Dacia,</hi> and by modern Potentates, <hi>Sigis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi> Emperor and <hi>Bajazet</hi> the first which was fatal to the Christians, and <hi>Michael</hi> the brave Vayvod of <hi>Valachia</hi> against <hi>Mahomet</hi> the third as calamitous and destructive to the Turks. Not to mention the plains of <hi>Cossova,</hi> where <hi>Miles Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belitz,</hi> a private Souldier rising from among the dead, slew <hi>Amu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rath</hi> the first: and for that three
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:208142:21"/> days incounter betwixt <hi>Huniades</hi> and <hi>Amurath</hi> the second, both of them with the adversest fortune that Christians ever fought with; which is to this day alledged as an argument against any Invasion up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Mahumetan Territory, how fondly, the encroachments of that enemy so many miles upon Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian ground doth sadly evince.</p>
               <p>And so we have finished the survey of <hi>Dacia,</hi> sometimes pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sessed by the <hi>Romans,</hi> afterwards by the <hi>Seythians,</hi> then by the <hi>Greek</hi> Emperors, and lastly swallowed by the Turks, who keep it so fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, that it will hardly know another Master.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Mount <hi>Haemus.</hi>
                  </label>Our next aspect tends towards <hi>Grecia;</hi> but in our way thither we must pass over Mount <hi>Haemus,</hi> so high and open to the weather, that it is said of it, that for eight months in the year it is always cold, for the other four winter. There are but two passes, and those thought so impregnable by
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:208142:21"/> their abruptness, that with little desence they are the invincible secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Turkish Dominion on the other side, as <hi>Huniades</hi> in his expedition to the seige of <hi>Hadrianople</hi> sadly experimented; but our Survey shall have leave and license to descend.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Graecia.</label>
                  <hi>GRECIA</hi> thus entertains our sight, which from the glorious and most noble structure of Empire, in the third universal Monarchy, a bridged afterwards by civil Fate, and the unwilling disrespect of time, into the Empire of the <hi>East,</hi> is crept into most petty and despi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Cantons of this barbarous Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niory, cut out and partitioned un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the commands of several infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riors, but most cruel Governors, all subjected to the Beglerbeg of <hi>Romania,</hi> so called by us, but by them <hi>Rum Ili.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the present Latitude &amp; extent thereof it is bounded on the <hi>East</hi> with the <hi>Propontick, Hellespont,</hi> and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:208142:22"/>
                  <hi>Aegean</hi> Seas, on the <hi>West</hi> with the <hi>Adriatick,</hi> on the <hi>North</hi> with Mount <hi>Haemus,</hi> which parteth it from <hi>Bulgaria, Servia,</hi> and part of <hi>Illy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium,</hi> on the <hi>South</hi> with the Sea <hi>Jonian,</hi> so that it is in a manner a Peninsula or Demy Island, environ'd on three sides by the sea, and on the fourth with the rest of Europe.</p>
               <p>To give precedency to Christia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity in the brief description of this Region, it will be satisfactory to give a little account of the Greek Church, (before-hand) in this part. The Patriarch of <hi>Constantinople,</hi> who was reckoned the last in order &amp; dignity, is now notwithstanding the principal &amp; chief of all, in point of latitude and power, which hath engrossed the most concerning af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of the Church to it self, for he presides over all <hi>Greece, Russia, Dacia, Sclavonia,</hi> part of <hi>Poland,</hi> and all the Islands in the <hi>Adratique</hi> adjacent Seas, which extent of jurisdiction confined at first within <hi>Thrace,</hi> was acquired
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:208142:22"/> by the reputation of the Imperial City for his See, and the diligence and piety of their Bishops in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versing and supplying the <hi>Russes</hi> and other Nations with Pastors and Ministers in such parts, which being conquered by the Turk, were forsaken by their Clergy, but such is the poor and despised condition thereof, that there is little power of Christian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And though it be enlarged in the outward Members it is much impaired at home, by the Tyranny of the Turks (who educate their Children in Mahumetanisme) on the one hand, and the Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of preferment unto Apostacy in the other, yet there are twenty Churches of them in <hi>Constantinople,</hi> and at <hi>Salonica,</hi> formerly <hi>Thessalonica</hi> thirty, which freely enjoy the profession of their faith.</p>
               <p>To return to <hi>Greece</hi> thus Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kified, it will be an unnecessary insignificant labour to trouble the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:208142:23"/> Reader with those several names, and particular numerous Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments thereof in former ages, when it produced the most martial and learned men, whose Ghosts would wish for annihilation at sight of the disgrace and ignominy of this their wretched posterity, we pass over the particular Dominions of old <hi>Sicyon,</hi> of <hi>Eli, Messenia, Sparta, Athens,</hi> now called <hi>Seli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> (and is but an ordinary Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough taken by <hi>Mahomet</hi> the great in 1440. when some beauty of it remained,) and in a general man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, since all limits of them are confounded in this barbarous sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection under the Grand Signior, and speak of those more noted places thereof, as they now pass under the name of <hi>Romania</hi> and are, Governed by one Viceroy as their supreme commander, ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Beglerbeg, of whom before a little; The next temporal Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in this Empire to the Prime or Grand Visier, as commanding
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:208142:23"/> the strength and flower thereof, as to its Martial and military Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>issance.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scriPtion of <hi>Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia.</hi>
                  </label>
                  <hi>TƲRKEY ROMANIA.</hi> And now that we have for brevities sake run over the Western Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of this mighty, rich, and dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Potentate, we will in some sort relate to the pleasure of the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, many the particulars of those good and ancient regions which at this day this <hi>Saraeenical</hi> Nation termeth by the name of <hi>Romania,</hi> so called, either for the many <hi>Roman</hi> Colonies planted there, or for the former name of <hi>Constanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople</hi> called <hi>Nova Roma.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This <hi>Romania</hi> at this day is the most populous and delecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blest part of the Turkish Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, and containeth the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces of <hi>Thrace,</hi> with it's <hi>Cherso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nese,</hi> vulgarly the straight of <hi>Calli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polis, Macedon, Epire</hi> now <hi>Alba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia, Achaia</hi> now <hi>Livadia, P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesus</hi> now <hi>Morea,</hi> and the Island of the <hi>Archipelago.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:208142:24"/>
               <p>
                  <label>The Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cissitudes of the Grecian Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</label> Until the coming of <hi>Cyrus</hi> King of <hi>Persia</hi> these Provinces remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in freedom, but of all others he first gave them the yoke of subjection. After him <hi>Xerxes</hi> the Son of <hi>Darius,</hi> with the succed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Princes of <hi>Persia</hi> did no less afflict them. When their turn was past, <hi>Philip</hi> King of <hi>Macedon</hi> acted his part, and united them under his own Dominion, until the days of <hi>Perseus,</hi> whom the <hi>Romans</hi> subdued and subjected. But the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire being di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided into the <hi>East</hi> and <hi>West,</hi> the <hi>Graecians</hi> began their Empire un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Constantine</hi> the Great, and Ruled honourably many ages, until the discent, first of the <hi>Goths,</hi> secondly of the <hi>Bulgares,</hi> thirdly of the <hi>Saracens,</hi> and lastly of the <hi>Turks,</hi> who slew their Emperor; and seized on the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire. Who at this day (except some relicks remaining under the <hi>Venetian</hi> Dominions,) possess the greatest part thereof, as well
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:208142:24"/> upon the continent as in the Islands. <label>The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the <hi>Greeks</hi>
                  </label> Those that are under the <hi>Venetian</hi> jurisdiction (saith <hi>Bellonius</hi>) little differ, especially in Religion, from those that are tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butary to the Turk: for both sorts being mingled, those that are subject to the <hi>Turks,</hi> live like <hi>Turks;</hi> and those that live under the <hi>Venetians,</hi> do as do the <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netians.</hi> So unspeakable is the rudeness of either, that through all their Cities you shall not find a School to instruct their youth. Promiscuously all speak the Greek tongue corrupted from the ancient, but some better then others. The <hi>Burghers,</hi> subject to the <hi>Italians,</hi> speak <hi>Italian</hi> as well as <hi>Greek,</hi> but the <hi>Villageois</hi> alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether <hi>Greek.</hi> And so the <hi>Graeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> which are subject to the <hi>Turk,</hi> in Cities speak <hi>Turkish</hi> and <hi>Greek,</hi> the <hi>Villageois</hi> onely <hi>Greek,</hi> and in places of traffique they bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row one from another, according as their business is with those
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:208142:25"/> whom they Negotiate. And as they differ in language, so do they in attire. Those that serve the <hi>Venetians</hi> go apparelled like <hi>Venetians,</hi> those that live under the <hi>Turk,</hi> like <hi>Turks.</hi> Both the Islanders and those that live on the continent as well in <hi>Europe</hi> as <hi>Asia,</hi> although subject to <hi>Turky,</hi> keep their ancient Christian faith. Long also they rejected the prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the Latine Church, and elected to themselves patriarchs, whom they acknowledge for their chief pastors, and appointed them several sees. Whom not onely the <hi>Grecians</hi> thus obey, but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise all those Provinces which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the <hi>Greek Church,</hi> as <hi>Circassia, Walachia, Bulgaria, Moscovia, Russia,</hi> the better part of <hi>Polonia, Mangrelia, Bosnia, Albania, Sclavonia,</hi> some part of <hi>Tartary, Sirtia, Croatia,</hi> and generally all the Provinces of the <hi>Euxin</hi> Sea. In number they are four, <hi>viz.</hi> the Patriarchs of <hi>Constantinople,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:208142:25"/> Alexandria, Jerusalem,</hi> and <hi>Antioch.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>The <hi>Gree<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> Patriarchs<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </label> Of these, the Patriarch of <hi>Constantinople</hi> is the Primat, sit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in <hi>Constantinople,</hi> and chiefly moderateth over the <hi>Caloieri</hi> (so are the <hi>Greek</hi> Priests termed) which reside in Mount <hi>Athos,</hi> and generally over all Christians, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessing the ritts of the <hi>Greek</hi> Church throughout <hi>Europe;</hi> and for the Monasteries of Mount <hi>Athos,</hi> and all other, dispersed over Europe, he payeth the Turk yearly 12000. ducats. The Patriarch of <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria</hi> moderateth in <hi>Aegypt</hi> and <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bia,</hi> and his dwelling places in <hi>Memphis</hi> and <hi>Cair,</hi> are not much inferior to his of <hi>Constantinople.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Patriarch of <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> absolutely moderateth in <hi>Judea,</hi> and over all professors of the <hi>Greek</hi> Religion throughout <hi>Siria.</hi> And must of necessity every year on the 15. of <hi>August,</hi> say Mass in the Monastery scituated upon Mount <hi>Libanus.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:208142:26"/>
               <p>The Patriarch of <hi>Antioch</hi> presi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in the Monasteries and the <hi>Greek</hi> Churches, which are in <hi>Beritus, Tripolis, Haleb,</hi> and other places of <hi>Asia.</hi> And in these places, as in all other, the Turk permitteth the Christians to use their consciences freely, so they perform their due and accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stomed tributes. To proceed,</p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Thrace</hi> d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed.</label>
                  <hi>THRACE</hi> hath on the <hi>East</hi> the <hi>Euxine</hi> Sea, the <hi>Thracian Bosphorus,</hi>
                  <hi> Propontis,</hi> and <hi>Helles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pont:</hi> on the <hi>North</hi> the Mount <hi>Haemus,</hi> upon the <hi>West</hi> the higher <hi>Mista,</hi> and part of <hi>Macedon,</hi> on the <hi>South</hi> the <hi>Archipelago.</hi> It is a most Noble Province, cold, plain and admirably populous, stored with grain, pulse and excellent wine, towards the Sea-side: but towards the up-land (lying more subject to cold) it is not so fertile nor wooddy.</p>
               <p>In it stands many goodly Cities <hi>Philipopolis, Nicopolis, So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phia,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:208142:26"/> Hadrianopolis,</hi> the former Regal Seat of the Turkish Kings, taken by <hi>Amurath</hi> the first, and beautified with a famous Seraglia. The Town is seated very plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>santly, and was built by <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drian</hi> the Emperour, whose name it retayns, it is now the usual retreat of this Grand Signior, and where at present he abides for its vicinity to his affayrs in <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary. Pera</hi> by others called <hi>Galata,</hi> once peopled by the <hi>Genoese,</hi> as the Mart and Factory of that State taken by <hi>Mahomet</hi> in 1653. but still replenished with Christian Merchants and Artificers.<label>Descripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the famous City of <hi>Constanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople.</hi>
                  </label> But above all other <hi>Constantinopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis,</hi> by Heaven erected to he the head of an Empire; as the onely seat which <hi>Romans, Greeks,</hi> and now the <hi>Turks,</hi> have chosen and reputed to be most commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously seated, not for the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment onely of the Empire, but (as was before generally men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned) of the whole world.</p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:208142:27"/>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Constinople</hi> described.</label>By its first Founders name it was called <hi>Byzantium,</hi> and after many various turns of Fortune betwixt the <hi>Persian</hi> and <hi>Spartans,</hi> it setled at last under the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, by the Conquest of <hi>Seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> who sacked it after three years siege, for their partaking with <hi>Niger</hi> his Competitor, but yet such Majesty remained in the very ruines, that <hi>Herodian</hi> reports, not without favour and pity there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, <hi>Mirabantur homines utrum eorum qui primi Extruxerunt vel eorum qui deinceps sunt demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liti vires essent potiores;</hi> it was wondred at, whether the strength of the Founders, or the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroyers was greatest. From this Rubbish it was reared and reedified by <hi>Constantine</hi> the Great, and finished <hi>May</hi> 11. 331. and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed with the Priviledges of <hi>Rome,</hi> and called for that reason <hi>Nova Roma</hi> for some short times, but in memory of its raiser, after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Constantinople.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:208142:27"/>
               <p>It continued in this state under the <hi>Eastern</hi> Empire 1100. years and upwards, till an unfortunate <hi>Constantine</hi> sirnamed <hi>Palaeologus,</hi> lost it to <hi>Mahomet</hi> the Great, <hi>A. D.</hi> 1453. by the base covetousness of the Citizens, who would not for their own defence supply the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror with money. It is eighteen miles in compass, by which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation it is one third part bigger then <hi>London</hi> and the <hi>Suburbs,</hi> it is said to contain seven hundred thousand souls, and would be much more populous were it not for the plague, whose <hi>Triennial</hi> mischief destroyeth multitudes, it is fortified toward the Land with three strong and high walls, the one higher then the other, but towards the sea with one onely built with many Turrets, which strongly flanker it. It yeilds a pleasant prospect a far off, by reason of the many Groves and Gardens within it, but is meanly built, the Houses but two sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:208142:28"/> high, some of course Stone, the rest of Timber, rough and ungarnished; there are in it 8000. Mosques or Churches, which are the beauty of the City, the chief of them, and worthy of remarque is that of St. <hi>Sophia,</hi> which in elegancy, though not in bulk exceeds all the Fabricks of the World, the sides and floor flagged with Marble, with a stately Porch at the entrance: add hereunto the Sepulchral Mosques of the Turkish <hi>Sultans,</hi> which are very sumptuous, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the <hi>Seraglio,</hi> built all of white Marble, round in form, and crowned at the top with shining golden Spires: not to omit the Mosque of <hi>Solyman</hi> the magnificent, one of the present wonders of the world. But <hi>Constantinople</hi> which is seated upon seven Hills and Mountains, as well as <hi>Rome,</hi> is better furnished with a Port and Haven, so conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient and advantageous to ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:208142:28"/> and so commodiously seated upon the <hi>Thracian Bosphorus,</hi> that Ships of all burdens, and with all winds may come close to the walls, the water is so deep. As to the Seraglio it standeth on one of the seven Hills in the <hi>Northeast</hi> quarter of the City, like a Delta two Angles of it aspect the Sea, which affords it a most pleasant spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation, the other is joyned by a wall to the City, towards which it hath one gate onely; the other gates are never opened but for the private pleasures of the Grand Seignior, or his displeasure to be executed by the death of some of his Officers and Bashaws; it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains three Courts, one within another, the first is open to all persons, in the second sits the Divan or Courts of Justice, into which no man comes on Horse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>back, the third is the Mansion and privacy of the Grand Signor and his women, it is three miles in circuit, in which are contained
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:208142:29"/> many delightful Groves of Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presses, intermixed with Plains, delicate Gardens, Artificial Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, Banquetting Turrets, and Prospect Rooms, with a most magnificent audience Chamber for Ambassadors, floored with embroydered Velvet seamed with Pearl and other Jewels. I have the longer insisted on this place, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause as the mistress of the World she draws all eyes upon her, and therefore it is fit to dress her in those Ornaments which she usu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally wears, and do become her greatness.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Callipolis,</hi> is another famous portion thereof, seated on the Northern promontory of <hi>Cherso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nese,</hi> the first City of note posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed by the Turks in <hi>Europe,</hi> taken in the reign of <hi>Orchanes</hi> in 1358. from whence they easily spread their conquest over the adjacent Provinces, it is the most convenient passage between <hi>Europe</hi> and <hi>Asia,</hi> by reason of the safe harbour and good anchorage.</p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:208142:29"/>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Macedon</hi> described.</label> Next followeth <hi>MACEDON,</hi> bounded on the East with the <hi>Aegae<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>an</hi> Sea, on the West with <hi>Albania,</hi> on the North with <hi>Mysia superiour,</hi> and on the South with <hi>Epyrus,</hi> and <hi>Achaia,</hi> is is now principally divided into <hi>Thessaly</hi> (a sweet and delectable Country) <hi>Macedon</hi> spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially so called, and <hi>Migdonia</hi> by the Turks called <hi>Iamboli.</hi> It is a fertile region inclosed with Hills, and neer the <hi>Jonian</hi> Sea, plain and woody. That it was once the Empress of the East, it is well known, but at this day it is Turkish, and without any famous Cities, save in a peice of <hi>Albania.</hi>
                  <label>Mount <hi>Athos.</hi>
                  </label> In it is nothing so memorable as the Mount <hi>Athos,</hi> or holy mount. It is seventy five miles in compass, three days journey long, and half a days journey broad, resembling the shape of a man lying with his face upward, whose highest cone, always covered with Snow, is seen thirty miles of at Sea. It is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeeding fertile in Grass, Fruit,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:208142:30"/> Oyl, and wine. <label>Priviledge of Greek Priests.</label>Long ago it was dedicated in honour of St. <hi>Basil</hi> to the Greek <hi>Caloieri,</hi> and endowed with priviledges, which at this day it enjoyeth by the Turks good favour; that is to say, that no man neither <hi>Grecian</hi> nor <hi>Turk</hi> may inhabit in this place except he be a Priest. So that their num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber in these days are about six thousand, dispersed into twenty four Monasteries, auncient and warlike, built for fear of Theeves and Pyrats, although there be no such great cause. In these Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steries are many reliques, which cause great concourse of people, and they are stately built, and richly adorned. This was made a <hi>Roman</hi> Province in the year of the world 3798. after the Capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity of their last <hi>King Perseus,</hi> and was upon the division of that Empire to East and West, consig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the Eastern, to which it continued subjected till <hi>Amurath</hi> rent it from that Dominion by
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:208142:30"/> taking <hi>Thessalonica,</hi> it is now go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned by a Sanjack, who is bound to maintain 100 horse, and to finde 400 more upon an Expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Epirus.</label>
                  <hi>Epire,</hi> now <hi>Albania,</hi> was once a very famous Province, bounded on the East with that part of <hi>Greece</hi> called <hi>Aetolia,</hi> on the West with the <hi>Adriatick,</hi> on the North with <hi>Thessaly, Macedon</hi> and part of <hi>Albania,</hi> and on the South with the <hi>Jonian</hi> Sea; as witnesseth <hi>P. Aemilius,</hi> it had in it seventy Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, now destroyed, and turned into ruines, and Villages meanly inhabited. For the most part it is woody and barren, but near the Sea fertile and adorned with very beautiful havens.</p>
               <p>This Country was formerly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous for <hi>Olimpias</hi> the Mother of <hi>Al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>xander</hi> the Great and <hi>Pyrrhus</hi> that great Captain among the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> but modernly as much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned for the unexemplary va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour and conduct of <hi>Scanderbeg</hi> or
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:208142:31"/>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Scanderbegs</hi> renown.</label> Lord <hi>Alexander,</hi> who proved a scourge to the Turks in the reigns of <hi>Amurath</hi> the second, and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homet</hi> the first, his bones after his death taken up, were worn by this rude enemy about them, as an omen or pledge of success and victory whomsoever they engaged with.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Achaia,</hi> mentioned for its name in Scripture, is a very goodly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, as may be gathered by the goodly Cities, which therein once flourished <hi>(viz.) Delphos, Thebs, Athens, Megara</hi> and many more, now destroyed.</p>
               <p>So is <hi>Peloponesus;</hi> termed by <hi>Pliny</hi> the Bulwark of <hi>Greece.</hi> It yeildeth all things that man can desire either for life or pleasure and although the ancient Cities be now defaced, yet is for quantity the best peopled part of <hi>Greece.</hi> It is now under the Turk, and counted the best Sang<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ackship in Turky, as bound to bring at the command of the <hi>Beglerbeg</hi> of <hi>Greece</hi> 1000
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:208142:31"/> horsemen under his own pay. It is worth yearly fourteen thousand ducats.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Dardanels.</label> And so we pass to the Isles of the adjoyning <hi>Aegean</hi> Sea, which are many in number, saluting first the <hi>Dardanels</hi> or the two Block<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houses, where all vessels passing out of the <hi>Hellespont</hi> into this Sea (which extends forty miles in length) are staid three days for slaves and other prohibited mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandizes, or until information of any such may come from <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantinople,</hi> they are exceedingly well walled, fortified and provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, they receive the customs, and are the principal strength of that City, as to the Mediterranean (as it is defended with the two black Towers (the Prison for the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shaws and great persons) at the mouth of the <hi>Euxine,</hi> where it joyns with the <hi>Thracian Bospho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> the one of which is scited a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove <hi>Constantinople</hi> on <hi>Europe</hi> side, and the other on the <hi>Asian</hi> shore.</p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:208142:32"/>
               <p>
                  <label>The <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geaan</hi> I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sslaups.</label>These <hi>Aegaean</hi> Islands are thus named <hi>Samothrace, Thassus, Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brus, Lemnos,</hi> famous for the late contest in 1660 between the Turks and Venetians about it, <hi>Euboea</hi> cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuiting a hundred and fifty miles in which stands the famous City known by the Gulf of <hi>Negropont,</hi> taken from the <hi>Venetians</hi> (to whom with other things it fell in the divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of the Eastern Empire unto the Latins) by Mahomet the Great in 1471. with the loss of forty thousand men. <hi>Salamis, Aegina,</hi> the <hi>Cyclades,</hi> in number fifty three, called now the Isles of the <hi>Arches,</hi> encompassing <hi>Delos</hi> and the <hi>Sporades.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Candia</hi> descr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bed.</label>Next we should veiw the Isles of the <hi>Cretan</hi> Sea, but they being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>considerable we will mention only <hi>Candia,</hi> in form extending <hi>East</hi> and <hi>West,</hi> in length two hundred and seventy, and in breadth fifty miles, placed in the midst of this
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:208142:32"/> Sea, the Natives speak the Greek Language, and before the Turks put foot there, were governed by Latine Bishops of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> to which the <hi>Venetians,</hi> then the Lords of it, do adhere.</p>
               <p>It hath been attempted by <hi>Selymus</hi> the second in 1571. when he conquered <hi>Cyprus,</hi> but in vain, yet <hi>Ibrahim</hi> the father of this Sultan, gained footing there some few years ago, and this is like when he shall be at leisure, unless the <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netians</hi> improve his absence in <hi>Hungaria,</hi> to carry it all; for of late he hath been very successful there against all the power they can make, and is at present pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sessed of the better half, so that he must be reckoned as more inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rested then the <hi>Venetian.</hi> The <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi> Isles as pertaining to their Seigniory, we are not obliged to mention here, though they stood in great danger of changing their Master.</p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:208142:33"/>
               <p>
                  <label>Rhodes.</label> From hence as we descend to the bottom of the straights appears the Island of <hi>Rhodes,</hi> (which we must observe in our way to the Isle of <hi>Cyprus,</hi> and so to <hi>Egypt</hi>) famous in former times for the potent residence of the Knights of the order of St. <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salem,</hi> who deserted by the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Princes were forced to yeild it in the Grand mastership of <hi>Ville<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius,</hi> to <hi>Solyman</hi> the Magnificent, not more to the scandal then detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Christianity, but this is so notorious that I must not enlarger my self.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Cyprus.</label>
                  <hi>Cyprus</hi> is situated in the <hi>Syrian,</hi> and <hi>Cilician</hi> Seas, extended in length from East to West two hundred miles, in breadth sixty, the whole Compass reckoned five hundred and fifty, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant from <hi>Cilicia,</hi> in <hi>Asia</hi> minor some sixty miles, it is a rich and fertile Kingdom, and hath in it twelve eminent Cities, but the most famous are those two of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:208142:33"/>
                  <hi>Nicosia</hi> and <hi>Famagusta,</hi> the last whereof was gallantly maintained by Signor <hi>Bragadino</hi> Governour of the Island, for the <hi>Venetians:</hi>
                  <label>The bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous conquest of <hi>Cyprus.</hi>
                  </label> who being in despair of releif, yeilded the Town, and consequently the Kingdom upon honourable. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles to <hi>Mustapha, Selymusses</hi> Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, but was barbarously fleaed alive, and all persons of quality murdered besides, onely a beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful Lady reserved for the lust of the Grand Signior, (with some other Prisoners) in their voyage to <hi>Constantinople</hi> blew her self, Ship and company into the Ayr, and worthily preserved and transmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted her honour to after ages invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olate.</p>
               <p>And so we pass to <hi>Syria. SYRIA</hi> is bounded on the <hi>South</hi> with <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lestina,</hi> and some parts of <hi>Arabia,</hi> on the West with the <hi>Mediterrane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> Sea, on the East with the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Euphrates,</hi> by which parted from <hi>Mesopotamia,</hi> on the <hi>North</hi> with <hi>Cilicia</hi> and <hi>Arm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nia</hi> minor,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:208142:34"/> from which it is separated by the mountain <hi>Taurus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Phaenicia</hi> described.</label> In the Survey of this spacious Country, the Reader is desired to limit his sight to the grand di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vision thereof into its several Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, wherein we must transito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily observe those Eminent Cities which are in the knowledge and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course of Europe; The first Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince is <hi>Phaenicia,</hi> bounded on the East and South with <hi>Palestine,</hi> on the North with <hi>Syria,</hi> on the West with the <hi>Mediterranean</hi> Sea. It is famous for the noble Cities (for their atcheivements and Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dises) of <hi>Tyre</hi> and <hi>Sydon, Berytus</hi> and <hi>Ptolemays,</hi> the last place of the Holy War Conquest: they were reduced to the Turkish Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mion in 1489. but that place which now most concerns us, is <hi>Tripoli,</hi> bravely and fertilely seated, once a Christian Marquisate (but in name so allied to that barbarous den of Theives in <hi>Africa,</hi> mischeivous to trade, that I cannot but forestal its
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:208142:34"/> scite) and is upon that account the Metropolis of <hi>Phaenicia:</hi> secondly <hi>Syria Propria,</hi> bounded and adjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Northward to <hi>Phenicia,</hi> famous to our acquaintance, for <hi>Laodicea,</hi> as is mentioned in the <hi>Revelations</hi> of Saint <hi>John;</hi>
                  <label>Antioch.</label> and <hi>Antioch,</hi> the place where Christians were first so called, but now hath no name it self either Turkish or Christian to be called by, being sunck into most obscure and ignote Rubbish. It was finally lost from the Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans is 1381. when it came to <hi>Saladine,</hi> the Victorious Sultan of <hi>Egypt</hi> and <hi>Damascus.</hi>
                  <label>Aleppo.</label> Thirdly <hi>Comagena</hi> bordering upon <hi>Euphra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> towards the East, with which it is watered, in it <hi>Aleppo</hi> scituated in midst betwixt <hi>Tripolis, Beritus,</hi> and <hi>Alexandretta,</hi> the three prime ports of <hi>Turkey,</hi> and on the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther side it adjoyns to the <hi>Persi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> Territories; it hath been of long time a factory of the English Nation, governed by a Consul who maintain thence correspondence
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:208142:35"/> with the East Indies, several goods comming overland upon Camels.<label>Aleppo.</label> The English are here well belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and our Tutelar or National Saint <hi>George,</hi> whose Sepulchre is fayned here, is had in great ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration; It overlooks by its situ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation upon a Hill six Villages, to be seen no where else in these depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulated uncultivated places of this Empire, and is governed by a Bashaw, which Dignity hath of late years been troublesome to the Turkish State, as was mentioned in the former part; It was taken in by <hi>Selymus</hi> the fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>st, of which more presently. Fourthly <hi>Palmyrene</hi> a Country never con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered in the Holy-Land expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as the other parts were. Fifthly, <hi>Coelosyria</hi> bounded on the West with <hi>Palaestine,</hi> whither we are next to pass, and on the South-East, with <hi>Arabia Deserta,</hi> and on the North with <hi>Palmyrene,</hi> remarquable for the famous City of <hi>Damascus,</hi> and the Imperial
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:208142:35"/> and regal Seat of many Kings, who have been celebrated as well in Divine as humane writ. <label>Damascus.</label> A most fruitful delightful place, even to surfeit, being stored with wine to superfluity, for which reason, as is excellently observed, the vile Impostor Mahomet would not be perswaded to come to it, lest being inescated with its pleasures he should forget the business he came about, but his Successors were not so abstemious, it being the seat of one of his Caliphs, while <hi>Babylon</hi> or <hi>Bagdat</hi> was reedified. Here are many ingenuous workmen in most Arts, and hence come our Damask Satins and Linnens, wrought with curious Branches. It is now the Seat of one of the principal Turkish Bashaws, and who is had in great estimation and beloved by the Grand Seig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor; It was held in modern times by the <hi>Mamalukes,</hi> who piece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meal recovered <hi>Syria</hi> from the <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> who under <hi>Tamberlane</hi> ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:208142:36"/> sacked this City; but in the year 1516. when the victorius <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limus</hi> the first discomfited <hi>Campson Gaurus</hi> the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Sultan in the fields of <hi>Aleppo,</hi> this City fearing the Spoyl and ruine there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of then very opulent by trade, set open their Gates, as did all the other Cities by their example. By means whereof the Turks became Lords of all this Country with out any more blows, as they were next year of <hi>Egypt</hi> also, by their victory over <hi>Tomombeius,</hi> in whom perished the Name and, Empire of the <hi>Mamalukes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Mount <hi>Hermon.</hi>
                  </label> In our way to <hi>Palestine</hi> on the Holy Land, we must pass over Mount <hi>Hermon,</hi> a ledge of Hills, which beginning Eastward run di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly South, by which <hi>Palestine</hi> is bounded on the East, and parted from <hi>Coelosyria</hi> and <hi>Arabia Deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta,</hi> on the West with the <hi>Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terranean</hi> Sea, and some part of <hi>Phaenicia;</hi> On the North it is divided with the Hill <hi>Anti-Liba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:208142:36"/> from <hi>Syria,</hi> and on the South with part of <hi>Arabia Petraea;</hi> a most fertile Land even to admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, flowing with milk and Hony, as it is elegantly expressed in the eight of <hi>Deuteronomy;</hi> by its former division it was can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toned into six Provinces. 1. <hi>Berea,</hi> 2. <hi>It<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rea,</hi> 3. <hi>Galilee,</hi> 4. <hi>Samaria,</hi> 5. <hi>Judea,</hi> and 6. <hi>Idumea,</hi> but made one Province of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, as it is now of the Turkish, the chief Cities were <hi>Coesarea, Samaria,</hi> and <hi>Hierusalem,</hi> of which a little must needs be spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken.</p>
               <p>For to speak nothing of ancient times, in the 73. year after Christ, <hi>Jerusalem</hi> was taken and destroyed by <hi>Titus,</hi> with the slaughter and captivity of infinite thousands. In the year 136. it was restored by <hi>Aelius Adrianus,</hi> new-named <hi>Aelia,</hi> and given in possession to the Jews. In the time of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantine</hi> and <hi>Helena</hi> his Mother, it fell into the hands of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:208142:37"/> and so continued untill the days of our <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, at which time it was again ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by the Sultan of the <hi>Sara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens,</hi> and the Christians clean ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Holy land.</label> In the year 1097. in a general Councel for the delivery of the Holy Land, the <hi>Crossed</hi> Knights were instituted throughout Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stendom, and <hi>Godfrey</hi> of <hi>Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loygne</hi> chosen General of three hundred thousand footmen, and one hundred thousand horse. These Knights did many famous acts; recovered the Land, instituted a Monarchy, and though sometime with loss, continued some defence thereof, until the year of our Lord 1517. and then was it over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come by the Turkish Armys, of the aforesaid victorious <hi>Selymus,</hi> who at this day retain it in misera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble servitude under a certain Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute or imposition upon such Christians as are permitted to live here.</p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:208142:37"/>
               <p>There are now therefore two or more Monasteries, or Religious Houses, where Fryars do abide, and make a good commodity of shewing the Sepulchre of Christ, and other Monuments unto such Christian Pilgrimes as do use super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitiously to go in Pilgrimage to the <hi>Holy Land.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And so it resteth peopled with men of divers Nations and Sects; as <hi>Saracens, Arabians, Turks, Hebrews,</hi> and Christians: whereof some follow the Latine Church, some the Greek: as the <hi>Grecians, Syrians, Armenians, Georgians, Nestorians, Jacobites, Nubians, Marodits, Abessines, Indians,</hi> and <hi>Egyptians,</hi> every one having their peculiar Bishops, whom they obey. But to particularize a little further.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>GALILIE</hi> upon the North is invironned with the steep hills of <hi>Libanus</hi> and <hi>Antilibanus,</hi> upon the West with <hi>Phenicia,</hi> upon the East with <hi>Caelosyria,</hi> and upon the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:208142:38"/> South with <hi>Samaria,</hi> and <hi>Arabia</hi> the desert. The soil is most fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, yeilding all sorts of trees, and divided by <hi>Jordan:</hi> upon whose banks stand very many Towns and Villages, and so w ll watered either with mountain Torrents, or springs, that no part thereof lyeth unmanured.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Nazareth.</label>The Country is the more fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, for that in it, standeth (amongst the rude mountains) the small Village of <hi>Nazareth,</hi> the place of our Lords conception: And at this day, there is a small Chappel Archt and built under ground, whereinto a man must descend by stayrs: Here (some say) the Angel appeared unto <hi>Mary,</hi> and foretold her that she should conceive and bring forth our Lord.</p>
               <p>The Inhabitants are <hi>Arabians,</hi> short and thick men, rudely ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parelled, and weaponed with Bows, Swords and Daggers. In this Region likewise standeth the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:208142:38"/> Mount <hi>Thabor,</hi> whose North part is inaccessible, and whereon our Lord was transfigured, according to the blessed Evangelist.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Samaria.</label>
                  <hi>SAMARIA</hi> lyeth in a most delicate plot of <hi>Palestine,</hi> but in bigness not comparable to <hi>Iudea</hi> or <hi>Galilie.</hi> The soyl is partly Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanous, partly champian, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant, fruitful, and very well watered with fresh and sweet water. The City is now ruinated: but as for pleasure and delight it was inferior to no other. It is scitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated upon the side of a Hill, the eighth part of a mile from whence, a man may behold the ruines of a great Temple: whereupon (as men say) Christ sate, when he asked water of the <hi>Samaritan</hi> wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. But these are uncertainties, not to say fallacies.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Judea.</label>
                  <hi>JƲDEA,</hi> far excelleth any part of the residue of <hi>Palestine,</hi> and at this day enjoyeth it's ancient fertility.</p>
               <p>The tribe of <hi>Juda</hi> so named it,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:208142:39"/> and in it, as in the rest of <hi>Pale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stina</hi> were very many worthy Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, <label>Jerusalem.</label> whereof <hi>Jerusalem</hi> was the chief seat of their Princes, the possession of the Patriarches, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and Apostles: the original place of our faith, and the glory of the Christian world. By the <hi>Barbarians,</hi> at this day it is called <hi>Godz,</hi> or <hi>Chutz:</hi> It standeth on an eminent place, as whereunto a man must always ascend.</p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Jeroms</hi> opinion was, that it stood not onely in the heart of <hi>Judaea,</hi> but in the very center of the world, as having <hi>Asia</hi> on the East, <hi>Europe</hi> on the West, upon the South <hi>Lybia</hi> and <hi>Africa,</hi> and upon the North, <hi>Scythia, Armenia, Persia,</hi> with the residue of the Pontique Nations.</p>
               <p>What the glory hereof hath been, may be conjectured out of <hi>Tacitus,</hi> who reporteth, that in the beginning of the Siege, it contained two hundred thousand souls. At this day it numbreth
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:208142:39"/> not above five thousand inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, although many Pilgrims daily resort thither in a good conscience, and for devotions sake.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchre of Christ.</label> It was once strongly and fairly walled, but now weakly, and therein it sheweth nothing so fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous as the Sepulchre of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour Christ, whose Temple in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circleth the whole Mount of <hi>Calvary,</hi> scituated upon a plain plot of ground, high, round, and open at the top, from whence it receiveth light: but the Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chre it self is covered with an archt Chappel cut out of the main Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and left unto the custody of the Latine Christians.</p>
               <p>Whosoever is desirous to see this Sepulchre, must pay nine Crowns to the <hi>Turk:</hi> so that this tribute is yearly worth unto him, a very considerable revevennue.</p>
               <p>One hundred and eight foot di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant from this Tomb, is the Mount (called the Mount <hi>Calvarie</hi>) where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:208142:40"/> our Saviour Christ was cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by the treacherous Jews. In this place are many other religious Reliques. And the Pilgrims which come thither, are always lodged according to his own profession; the Latines with the <hi>Franciscans,</hi> without the City, by Mount <hi>Syon:</hi> the Graecians are lodged with the <hi>Caloirean</hi> Greeks, dwelling within the City by the Sepulchre: And so every other Nation, <hi>Abessines, Georgians, Armenians, Nestorians,</hi> and <hi>Maronites,</hi> who all have their proper and peculiar Chappels. Those Franciscans, which follow the Latine Church, and are for the most part <hi>Italians,</hi> were wont to create the Knights of the Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, and to give testimonial unto Pilgrims of their being there.</p>
               <p>Without this City is the valley of <hi>Jehosaphet,</hi> and therein the Tombs of the blessed Lady and Saint <hi>Anne.</hi> The territory adjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is exceeding fruitful in Vines, Apples, Almonds, Figs and Oyl:
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:208142:40"/> the mountains are no less stored with trees, wild beasts and spiceries.</p>
               <p>Besides <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> here stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <hi>Bethlem,</hi> now destroyed, and shewing nothing worth looking on, save a great and stately Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stery of the <hi>Franciscans,</hi> within which is the place where Christ was born. <hi>Rama</hi> is now likewise ruinated; the Arches and Cisterns which are now remaining, by the witness of <hi>Bellonius</hi> his own eye, are greater then those of <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria,</hi> but not so thick.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gaza</hi> is now a Turkish <hi>Sangiack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship:</hi> the soyl about fertile, and the inhabitants <hi>Grecians, Turks,</hi> and <hi>Arabians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Idumea.</label>
                  <hi>IDƲMEA.</hi> I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oly writ, this Region is called <hi>Edom,</hi> and by other Authors <hi>Nabathea.</hi> Toward the Sea and <hi>Judea</hi> the soil is fertile, but toward <hi>Arabia</hi> desert and bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren. Some say its inexpugnable for its deserts and want of water: yet is it stored therewith but hidden, and known to none but the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives.
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:208142:41"/> Of old they were a turbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, unquiet, and seditious peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and so at this day they are like to their villanous and roguish Neighbours the <hi>Arabians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For further satisfaction of the Reader, be he pleased to refer him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self to Doctor <hi>Fullers</hi> Holy Land, or Sir <hi>Walter Raleigh,</hi> who have amply discoursed on this Subject, by whose copious and pleasant stile and luxurious description, the Ruines and present indigence and penury of this once flourishing and abundant Region are only to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leviated. And so we pass forward.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Egypt.</label>
                  <hi>AEGYPT</hi> is best to be known as to its bounds, by its threefold defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition and division. First, <hi>Egypt</hi> properly so called, extends it self North upon the <hi>Mediterranean</hi> sea, and part of <hi>Idumea</hi> to <hi>Lybia</hi> or <hi>Marmarica.</hi> Secondly, <hi>Lybia</hi> or <hi>Marmarica</hi> lying betwixt <hi>Egypt</hi> properly so called, and <hi>Cyrene</hi> or <hi>Pentapolis,</hi> so called for the five
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:208142:41"/> cheif Cities thereof, 1300 miles long and 200 broad, reaches from <hi>Lybia</hi> to the Greater <hi>Syrty,</hi>
                  <label>The king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of <hi>Tunis</hi> and <hi>Algeir.</hi>
                  </label> where it is bounded with the Kingdom of <hi>Tunis</hi> in <hi>Africa,</hi> which Kingdom with the other of <hi>Algeir,</hi> by the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Family's intermedling with the quarrelling Princes thereof, though Mahumetans also, came at length to acknowledge no other Master but themselves, the last King of <hi>Tunis</hi> named <hi>Mahomet,</hi> put in by Don <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Austria</hi> whose succour he craved, being subdued by the Turks, and carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed prisoner to <hi>Constantinople</hi> in the reign of <hi>Selymus</hi> the second, about which time the Kingdom of <hi>Algeir</hi> in length 300 miles, but in breadth not considerable, was likewise re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced upon the same score by the famous <hi>Barbarossa.</hi> Not to men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion here some of the Isles of <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bary</hi> which are subject to the Grand Seignior, as <hi>Zerby,</hi> infamous for the loss of 15000 Christians by slaughter at the taking, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:208142:42"/> by famine at the sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize and retaking of it by <hi>Pial</hi> Bassa in 1559. I am constrained to mention these parts of <hi>Affrick</hi> here, for want of convenient re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction (in this brief Compendium) to their proper place.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aegypt</hi> was vassalled to the <hi>Mamalukes,</hi> who seized it from the Eastern Emperors some 300 years before <hi>Selimus</hi> the second, that ambitious and martial Sultan wrested it from them in the fields of <hi>Aleppo,</hi> and extinguished the name and Empire as aforesaid: When <hi>Cyrene</hi> followed the same fortune, and submitted to the Turkish yoke. In this Province we must remarque <hi>Tripolis,</hi> assign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>Charls</hi> the fift to the Knights of <hi>John of Jerusalem</hi> in lieu of <hi>Rhodes,</hi> but wrested from them by <hi>Sinan</hi> Bassa in 1577. since which it is become a den of Pirates, as was mentioned before in the <hi>Syri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Tripolis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In <hi>Egypt,</hi> passing over <hi>Pelusium</hi>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:208142:42"/> and the famous <hi>Damiata,</hi> we will confine our view to <hi>Grand Cairo,</hi> once called <hi>Memphis,</hi> the Metropo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis of <hi>Egypt,</hi> which of all antient Cities hath lost little or nothing by the injury of time.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Grand Cairo</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed at large.</label> Grand <hi>Cairo</hi> was wrested from the <hi>Mamalukes,</hi> and their Sultan <hi>Tomombeus,</hi> by <hi>Selymus</hi> the first in the year of the Incarnation, 1517. after four bloody days spent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he could entirely possess him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self of the City; It is nobly scited, and is between thirty and forty English Miles in compass, devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into seven Burghs, built after the <hi>Egyptian</hi> manner, high, and of large rough stone, part also of Brick, the streets are narrow, of late there are new buildings made of the Turkish Fashion as the former decay, poor, low much of Wood and Timber, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept some modern stately palaces of both Nations.</p>
               <p>There are in it as are reckoned five and thirty thousand Moschets,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:208142:43"/> four and twenty thousand noted streets, besides lanes and turnings, some of those streets are two miles in length, some not half a mile, all of them every night are lockt up with a Door or Gate at each end, and Guarded by a Musketier, to prevent Tumults, Fire, or other outrages.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Its Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</label>Without the City on horse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>back there watch every night to prevent any attempts of the <hi>Arabs,</hi> four Sanjacks, with each a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand Horse-men under his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, so that in all, as it is easily computable by the indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidual, Guardians of the streets there watch every night no less then twenty eight thousand per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons.</p>
               <p>The Castle is the place where the Bashaw resides, who is always one of the most avaricious and ravenous Viziers, sent thither on purpose to squeeze and oppress the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> and is frequently made a Spunge, to refund his wealth
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:208142:43"/> with his life) into the Grand Seig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niors Exchequer, in which act the slavish <hi>Egyptians</hi> can discern nothing but his justice, and are satisfied with it as their revenge. This Castle is founded upon a Rocky ascent on the East side of the City, nor well repayred nor quite decayed; at the foot of this ascent is a place half a Mile long, wherein they ride the great horse, and by that a little House and Garden, (wherein the old Bashaws of this place, when disauthorised till the coming of a new one, are kept until they are strangled or restored to the Grand Signors favour. <label>The fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Nile.</hi>
                  </label>Things of remarque and note herein, are first the River <hi>Nile</hi> running along the South of the Town to the West, making as it leaves it, a little dainty Island, whose fertile and wonderful inun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation begins constantly about the middle of <hi>June,</hi> and increaseth to between eighty and a hundred days, then it abates, and by the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:208142:44"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:208142:44"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:208142:45"/> end of <hi>November</hi> comes within its narrowest banks, about a quarter of a mile broad: by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of this flood they have four Harvests in a year, the ground ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jacent to this River being before a white Sand, without a sprig of any green thing but two weeds (which carried to <hi>Venice</hi> makes the finest Chrystal Glass) becomes a fat black mould, and bears Flax and Rice, with Sugar-Canes in abundance. Not to omit the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Crocodiles that infest this River, nor the <hi>Nilscope</hi> in the Isle, where stands a Pillar with several marks, declaring the height of the Flood all over <hi>Egypt.</hi>
                  <label>The Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramids.</label> The next are the Pyramids so much famed in history, and the granaries or store<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houses which <hi>Joseph</hi> built, three of which Pyramids stand twelve miles South-west of the City on the other side of the River, and are yet almost entire, their form is quadrangular, lessening by equal degrees from a quarter of a
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:208142:45"/> mile flat at bottom to a square at top a little more then 4. yards an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular; there are sixteen or eighteen other Pyramids some twelve miles to the Southward, but ruined ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly. It rains not here but once in three or four years, so that bodies buried in that sand, will keep without putrefaction, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son no moysture is near them but what is in themselves.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Cairo</hi> Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to plagues, yet popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous.</label> Plagues are here very rife in Winter, by one whereof eighteen hundred thousand pers<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns died in six months, yet was the City pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently as populous as before, and continues so thronged that persons of quality have one going before their Mules to make way for them, by bidding people make room, this is caused by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluent multitude of the <hi>Arabs,</hi> and <hi>Indians</hi> too, that flock to the pleasures and plenty of this place. There are a great many Christians also, <hi>Venetians, Dutch, Genoese,</hi> and some <hi>English,</hi> the
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:208142:46"/> ayr sometimes in summer is like any sweet perfume, and almost suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>focates the Spirits, caused by the wind that brings the odours of the <hi>Arabian</hi> Spices in a full Flavour.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy playns about it.</label> There is also a sort of rare Horses, but of tender hoofs, yet fit for that sandy and soft ground, which will run four days and Nights together with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out eating or drinking, and some <hi>Egyptians</hi> with a little pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, and less sleep, their body being wound about with a Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen, will ride them so upon busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, to which this is the only con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience, over those sandy deserts, where there is neither House or Inhabitants, but the Theiving Murderous <hi>Arabs.</hi> For the directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the way over those Vasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes, the wind blowing the Sand, and losing the track of any bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten way, and sometimes burying the Travellers in Sheats of it, unless they be wary, are pillars of
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:208142:46"/> brick, set up a mile distant from one another.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue of <hi>Egypt.</hi>
                  </label> The Revenue that the Grand Signor receives from <hi>Aegypt</hi> amounts to eight hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand pound sterling, a third part whereof comes onely clear to the Exchequer at <hi>Constantinople,</hi> all ariseth out of certain farms of the Land belonging to the Crown, let out to the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> the least farm pays two hundred pound a year. But the Bashaw hath other wayes to make profit to himself, nor is any invention of op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression thought envious or dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous; for the <hi>Egyptians</hi> natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally effeminate, and having suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered under a lasting Tyranny, from slavery to slavery, are in no likelihood of endeavouring a revolt: the Grand Signor hath of them no more then fourteen thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand enrolled in his pay, and that for show onely. The other two parts of the Revenue are disposed thus, the one to furnish the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:208142:47"/> of the Caravan and Pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage to <hi>Mecha,</hi> whither the Grand Seignor sends presents yearly, especially a green velvet Pall, for Mahomets Coffin, and the other third part of the revenue towards defraying the charges of the Government, <hi>viz.</hi> all Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers and publique services, besides that of the <hi>Timariots,</hi> who do theirs for their Tenure, and enjoy almost a half of that Kingdom. It is a rare felicity for any Bashaw of this place to escape with life, fortunes, and liberty, yet there are few of the Visiers, who do not ambitiously affect this ominous government.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ria.</label> The <hi>Nile</hi> descends from <hi>Cairo</hi> in a length of 360. miles to <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopus,</hi> now called <hi>Rosetta,</hi> where it embogues it self into the Sea: from whence by Land to <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria,</hi> the Port where goods are landed for <hi>Cairo,</hi> famous for its founder <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great, and for the Monument and Tomb of
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:208142:47"/> red Marble of its beautifier, <hi>Pompey</hi> the great, likewise, and for its new Castle built since by the Turks, being their onely Empo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium or scale of Trade in <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scription of <hi>Arabia.</hi>
                  </label>
                  <hi>ARABIA TRIPLEX.</hi> The three <hi>Arabias,</hi> are likewise parcel of this Empire, which is a marvel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous great country, included be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween two huge bosomes of the Sea, in manner of a <hi>Peninsula, viz.</hi> upon the West and East with the <hi>Arabian</hi> and <hi>Persian</hi> gulfs, upon the South with the Ocean, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the North with <hi>Syria</hi> and <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrates.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Inhabitants are indifferently called <hi>Arabians, Saracens,</hi> or <hi>Moors:</hi> Those are the true <hi>Arabians</hi> which live out of Cities in Tents, dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>persed over <hi>Syria, Egypt,</hi> and <hi>Afrike,</hi> these give themselves to feed Cattel, and droves of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mels. Those which inhabit Cities, are called <hi>Moors,</hi> and were once
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:208142:48"/> of such puissance, that they not onely subdued <hi>Syria, Persia,</hi> and <hi>Trogladitica,</hi> but likewise <hi>Egypt,</hi> a great part of <hi>Africk,</hi> and almost all <hi>Spain,</hi> with the Island of <hi>Sicily,</hi> and the Kingdom of <hi>Naples.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Two hundred years they kept possession of these peeces, but of some part of <hi>Spain</hi> seven hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, even until the days of our Fathers. And further, this accursed generation at this day is not onely spread over all the Southern coast of <hi>Asia: viz. Persia, East-India,</hi> and the Islands of the <hi>Indian</hi> Sea, but likewise advanced with great prosperity unto divers wealthy Kingdoms, famous Cities, and worthy Mart-towns, over all the South Coast of <hi>Africk:</hi> under this people the <hi>Turks</hi> were first called into <hi>Asia</hi> to bear Arms, and from whence issued out the swarm of this Locust <hi>Mahomet.</hi> The Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion is as followeth, first</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ision of <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </label>
                  <hi>ARABIA DESERTA.</hi> This is a vast Country, full of Deserts,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:208142:48"/> yet well inhabited with populous and warlike multitudes, especially toward <hi>Euphrates,</hi> and the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of <hi>Arabia Felix,</hi> whether Merchants resort. The residue towards the West is sandy, by which if a man be to travel, he must have the stars for his guide, company for his safeguard, and provision for his diet, for other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise he shall lose his way, or sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render his goods to the Theevish <hi>Arabs,</hi> or starve in the Desert for want of food.</p>
               <p>ARABIA PETREA. Towards <hi>Syria</hi> this is somewhat fertile, but smally commended for that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty by the Auncients: For in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it is exceeding barren, and wanteth necessary sustenance, wood and fresh water. The memorable things herein are the Mountains at <hi>Synay</hi> and <hi>Oreb,</hi> upon the former whereof, is at this day builded a Monastery of Christians, following the Greek
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:208142:49"/> Church, and the onely receptacle or Inn for wayfaring Christians: other place of releif is there none.</p>
               <p>ARABIA FELIX is a very large province, better manured and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered then the other. It is adorned with noble Cities, and full of Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lages, especially toward the Sea side, where are many excellent places of trade. The residue except the Sand, is made manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, either for feeding of Cattle or Camels, in which places live infinite swarms of divers Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, by Grazing and Husban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>s Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>y.</label>
                  <hi>Arabia Petrea</hi> and <hi>Deserta,</hi> were subdued by the <hi>Turks</hi> upon their first Conquest of <hi>Persia,</hi> in the rise of their greatness, but recovered by the <hi>Mamalukes,</hi> whose fortune they followed to the fatal period made by <hi>Selymus</hi> the first, when in his expedition to <hi>Egypt</hi> they more annoyed him by falling in his
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:208142:49"/> Rear, and terrified him in their night alarums, then all the Forces of their <hi>Mamaluke</hi> Masters in the field; which deciding the Title to <hi>Egypt</hi> included soon after the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion of those Countrys, the Chiefs thereof being gained by money and promise of prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, who yet nevertheless con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue their petty Soveraignties, and rob and steal upon their own account, making no distinction betwixt Turk and Christian.</p>
               <p>As for <hi>Arabia Faelix</hi> it continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unconquered, till the <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Portugals</hi> quarrelled about it in 1538. when <hi>Solyman</hi> Bassa sent with a Fleet into the red Sea to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the Trade thereof, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press the <hi>Persians,</hi> assisted by the said Portugals, instead of taking in, <hi>Diu,</hi> most basely surprized <hi>Aden,</hi> one of the chiefest Ports, when under colour of a friendly invitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he had got the King thereof on board, where he hanged him, as he did the like to <hi>Zibel</hi> (and the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:208142:50"/> King thereof) the Port of <hi>Mecca;</hi> nevertheless the Turks have but little command here, especially in the more inland pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ts, and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the <hi>Persian</hi> Gulf, where a <hi>Turk</hi> is generally hated and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Assiria</hi> described.</label>
                  <hi>ASSYRIA</hi> is bounded on the East with <hi>Media,</hi> West with <hi>Mesopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamia,</hi> South with <hi>Susiana,</hi> and North with part of <hi>Turcomania,</hi> by the last name of it as allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to its great Original, called by the Turks <hi>Arzyrum,</hi> and though formerly the terrible name of a mighty Empire, and the first of the four, is now a mean Province of the Grand Seigniors Dominion: <label>
                     <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>inivie.</label> in it was once seated the famous City of <hi>Nineve</hi> mentioned in Scripture, but the name and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of it is now lost, only it is supposed that Mosul seated on the <hi>Tygris,</hi> and inhabited with a number of <hi>Nestorian</hi> Christians is risen out of its ruines. The Bassa of <hi>Arzyrum,</hi> the chief and
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:208142:50"/> strongest place in this Province, hath ten thousand <hi>Timariots</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his Command to defend this Country, and to be ready for any other service.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>MESOPOTAMIA</hi> is bounded on the South with <hi>Arabia Deserta,</hi> from which it is parted with the bending of <hi>Euphrates,</hi> on the East with the River <hi>Tygris</hi> &amp; <hi>Assyria,</hi> on the West with <hi>Syria,</hi> on the North with Mount <hi>Taurus,</hi> and <hi>Arme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia Major,</hi> it is memorable for very little of modern note, the people prone to slavery, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of any Master that can win and wear them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>CHALDEA</hi> bounded on the East with <hi>Susiana</hi> a Province of <hi>Persia,</hi> on the West with <hi>Arabia De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serta,</hi> on the <hi>North</hi> with <hi>Meso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potamia,</hi> and on the South with the <hi>Persian Bay,</hi> and the rest of the <hi>Deserta.</hi> As to the account hereof we shall confine our view to <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi>
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:208142:51"/>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Babylon</hi> described.</label> enlarged by <hi>Nebuchadnezzer,</hi> once accounted one of the worlds nine wonders, but since dwindled into oblivion, but recovered by the name first of <hi>Seleucia,</hi> and now of <hi>Bagdat:</hi> it was taken from the <hi>Persians</hi> by <hi>Solyman</hi> the Magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, and recovered from them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Sophy Abbas</hi> in 1625. and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken from them by the noble and glorious <hi>Sultan Morat</hi> in 1640. when he intended to bury the name of the <hi>Janizaries</hi> in the rubbish of it, but left his own bones there like another <hi>Alexander:</hi> but the same vicissitude hath again restored it to this present Sophy; the people of those Regions as washinted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, being patient and regardless of any power or Government what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever, as sure to suffer no worse, nor having ever experienced better.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>urcoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ia.</label> TURCOMANIA (of which some thing more largely for the quality of the place) is bounded on the North with part of <hi>Tartary,</hi> upon the West with the <hi>Euxine</hi> Sea, <hi>Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>padocia</hi>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:208142:51"/> and <hi>Armenia Minor,</hi> on the East with <hi>Media</hi> and the <hi>Caspian</hi> Sea, and on the South with <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sopotamia</hi> and <hi>Assyria,</hi> it is called <hi>Turcomania</hi> from the Turks, who from hence made their first fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate expedition and irruption to the conquest of <hi>Persia,</hi> and spread themselves afterwards into other Regions. The Inhabitants are now generally Christians, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledged by <hi>Mahomet</hi> the Great, and speak a language of their own, yet are their manners ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry barbarous, given much to Tillage, and very industrious; they are of late well seen in Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nufactures, especially in rich Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pestries, Grograins, and watered and unwatered Chamlets, with which they Traffick in all places of Turkey.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Armenia Major.</label>The chief Provinces of this Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritory, are <hi>Armenia Major,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered by <hi>Selymus</hi> the first in 1515. after the fatal <hi>Calderan</hi> field, the day whereof was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:208142:52"/> by the Turks Dooms-day, against <hi>Hismael</hi> the <hi>Persian Sophy,</hi>
                  <label>The <hi>Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dean</hi> fields</label> whose Predecessor <hi>Ʋssan Cassan</hi> took it from a Christian Prince thereof; and fully setled by <hi>Amurath</hi> the third, by the strong Garrison of <hi>Van.</hi> 2. <hi>Colchis,</hi> reduced by <hi>Ʋluzales</hi> the famous <hi>Turkish</hi> Sea Captain, sent into the <hi>Euxine</hi> Sea by <hi>Amurath</hi> in 1579. and made subject to a Beglerbeg. 3. <hi>Iberia</hi> with the rest, formerly feudatory to the <hi>Grecian,</hi> as before to the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, by the same <hi>Amurath</hi> (who pursued his Father <hi>Solymans</hi> design) was partly united to his Scepter, but the <hi>Georgian</hi> Princes by the neer ayd of the <hi>Persians</hi> have yet a part. 4. <hi>Albania</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered by the Great Cham of <hi>Tartary,</hi> but since blended with the other <hi>Georgians</hi> into Turkish slavery. This <hi>Turcomania,</hi> though it were the first place of the Turks ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction, yet it was the last of their conquest, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sides that it is
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:208142:52"/> strangely Christian, and is the last Province that is assured and setled under their Dominion.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Georgia</hi> described.</label>GEORGIA, by the <hi>Barbarians</hi> tearmed <hi>Gurgistan,</hi> comprehendeth part of the ancient <hi>Iberia,</hi> with part of the great <hi>Armeny,</hi> and peradventure <hi>Atrapatia.</hi> Upon the West lyeth <hi>Mengrelia,</hi> upon the North <hi>Zuiria</hi> (once <hi>Albania</hi>) up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the East the middle <hi>Atropatia</hi> (now <hi>Sirvan</hi>) upon the South that part of the greater <hi>Armenia,</hi> which now is called <hi>Turcoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the greater part it is cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with Mountains, Woods, and Thickets, and in that regard inconquerable, for the difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Mountanous passages. It is notwithstanding fertile, and adorned with many large places and villages, from whence arise many famous Rivers, as <hi>Cirus</hi> and <hi>Araxis,</hi> springing from the Mountain <hi>Taurus,</hi> and running thorough the whole Province, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:208142:53"/> at last, it disgorge it self into the <hi>Caspian</hi> Sea.</p>
               <p>The Inhabitants are tearmed <hi>Georgians,</hi> of St. <hi>George,</hi> whom they advow their patron and advocate. For they are Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans according to the Greek Church, with some small diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence. They are very populous and warlike, strong of body, and valorous in fight, even until our times maintaining their liberty in the midst of the Mahumetans, sometimes following the fortunes of the Turks, sometimes of the <hi>Persians.</hi> But at this day, they have not onely lost their wonted liberty, but also many Fortresses and Cities, as <hi>Teflis, Lori, Clisca, Gori,</hi> and <hi>Tomanis,</hi> and withal some of them have imbraced the Turkish infidelity.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The City <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>f <hi>Tauris.</hi>
                  </label>I must here insert the noble City of <hi>Tauris</hi> in <hi>Media,</hi> within that Province belonging to the <hi>Persian,</hi> being the utmost extent of the Turkish Dominion Eastward, and
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:208142:53"/> the bound thereof, whither being arrived we will return back to <hi>Constantinople</hi> by the way of <hi>Asia Minor,</hi> called <hi>Natolia,</hi> and after this spacious perambulation, sit down and compute in an intire sum, the whole extent of this Dominion, for the reader happily may be tyred with so tedious a journey.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Asia</hi> Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor.</label>
                  <hi>NATOLIA.</hi> That which the Turks at this day term <hi>Natolia</hi> or <hi>Turcia Major,</hi> once <hi>Asia Minor,</hi> comprehendeth the Provinces of <hi>Pontus, Bithinia, Asia</hi> it self, <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia, Galacia, Pamphilia, Cappa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>docia, Cilicia,</hi> and <hi>Armenia</hi> the less; and in these Provinces of antient times florished the States and Kingdoms of the <hi>Troyans,</hi> of <hi>Methridates,</hi> of <hi>Cressus,</hi> of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigonus,</hi> of the <hi>Paphlagonians,</hi> of the <hi>Galathians,</hi> of the <hi>Capadoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> and <hi>Phrigians;</hi> All which at this day are not sufficient to satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the single ambition of the Turkish Tyranny. The Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants for the most part are Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humetans,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:208142:54"/> and naturally Turks, of simpler nature then the Turks of <hi>Europe,</hi> and nothing so cruel as the <hi>Renegado</hi> Christians. <label>The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</label> Yet are there many Christians among them in many of these Regions, following the Rites of the Greek Church. Among these Turks there is no acknowledgment of Superiority, Blood or Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but all are equal slaves to the Grand Signior, over whom he appointeth Beglerbegs and Sanjacks. They are either a kind of idle or lofty people, for they are smally industrious, and were it not for their slaves, their grounds would generally lye un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manured.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Its Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons.</label>
                  <hi>Pontus</hi> and <hi>Bithynia</hi> are now united under one name, and called <hi>Bursia.</hi> Here once raigned the Great King <hi>Methridates;</hi> and here stood the Famous Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of <hi>Chalcedon, Nichomedia, Apamia, Prusia Nice,</hi> and <hi>Hera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clea Ponti.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:208142:54"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Asia propria,</hi> now <hi>Sabrum,</hi> is a particular Province of <hi>Asia minor,</hi> and containeth in it many famous Provinces, as <hi>Phrygia major,</hi> and <hi>minor, Caria, Mysia, &amp;c.</hi> in <hi>Phry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gia minor</hi> stood that noble City of <hi>Troy,</hi> famous at this day (saith <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonius</hi>) an eye witness, for it is very ruines of walls, gates, cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circuit and marble sepulchres, found upon the way without the walls.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pamphylia</hi> now <hi>Caramania,</hi> is one of the seven Sangiack-ships, with 8000 ducats of yearly reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue, In this Country, as also in <hi>Cilicia,</hi> are woven those fine cloaths which we call Chamblets, watered and unwatered. They are made of the hair of Goats, so fine and white as no silk can surpass them in those two properties.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire of <hi>Trapezond.</hi>
                  </label>
                  <hi>Cappadocia</hi> now <hi>Amasia,</hi> is a goodly Country, and the seat of the Turks eldest Son. In it are many goodly Cities, as <hi>Trapezond</hi> once the seat of the <hi>Commeni,</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:208142:55"/> of <hi>Trapezond,</hi> whose name and progeny, <hi>Mahumet</hi> the second utterly extinguished.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cilicia,</hi> now part of <hi>Carama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi> is a good Country; the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants are given to pasturing of Goats for lucre of their fleece, of which they make their Chamblets; but otherwise neither given to fish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Navigation nor Husbandry. At the foot of mount <hi>Taurus</hi> (saith <hi>Bellonius</hi>) are divers small Villages, and excellent pastures a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout them, which for the fertility thereof should seem to be one of the Turks Races; for from thence he culleth out every year 600 horse of service, which they high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly esteem, and name <hi>Carama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Armenia minor,</hi> is a better soil, and more populous then <hi>Cappa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>docia,</hi> round about incircled with tall, huge, broken and woody mountains. These Provinces are of <hi>Natolia,</hi> governed by a <hi>Beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerbeg,</hi> the cheif next to him of <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mania,</hi>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:208142:55"/> but his forces are not estee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med so much for their service as the Europeans.</p>
               <p>The whole is bounded on the East with the River <hi>Euphrates,</hi> by which it is parted from <hi>Asia</hi> the Greater, on the West with the <hi>Thracian Bosphorus</hi> and <hi>Hellespont,</hi> by which divided from <hi>Europe,</hi> on the North with the <hi>Euxine</hi> Sea, and on the South by the <hi>Rhodian, Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian,</hi> and <hi>Pamphilion</hi> Seas, so that it is almost a demy Island or Penin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sula. <label>The Island <hi>Rhodes.</hi>
                  </label> To omit for brevity sake thr Provinces of the Isles, among which are reckoned as chief, <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos, Lesbos, Tenedos,</hi> and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally <hi>Rhodes,</hi> an Island an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and forty miles in compass, the City whereof, taken by <hi>Soly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> the magnificent on Christmass day 1522. is reputed one of the most impregnable Fortresses the Turks possess, as is <hi>Famagusta</hi> in <hi>Cyprus.</hi> It is now inhabited by Turks and Jews which were banisht out of <hi>Spain.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:208142:56"/>
               <p>As to the story of <hi>Anatolia,</hi> it chiefly depends upon the ruines of the two Empires of <hi>Constantinople</hi> and <hi>Trabezond,</hi> and the Kingdom of <hi>Caramania,</hi> subdued by <hi>Bajazet</hi> the second, since which time every parcel thereof became united to the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Dominions. It was once the most flourishing part of the world, but hath lost since some few Centuries, no less then 4000. Cities, partly by earth-quakes, which are frequent here, and partly by the sloth and natural laziness of the Turks, who busie themselves in nothing but their lust and luxu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, so that little Trade is stirring here. But their Horse bred here retain their native excellency, and are reputed the best, the Europe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Horse-men are likewise so estee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. And in these two consist the chief power and strength of the Turk.</p>
               <p>So that we have s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en under the Empire of the Turk i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hended the better part of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="99" facs="tcp:208142:56"/> antient threefold division of the earth, which we will recapitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late and repeat for the Readers memory. <label>The sum of the Turkish dominions</label> He holdeth in Europe the whole Sea coast, which from the borders of <hi>Epidaurus,</hi> stretches it self to the mouth of <hi>Tanais:</hi> whatsoever lyeth between <hi>Buda</hi> and <hi>Constantinople,</hi> and from the <hi>Euxine</hi> Sea to the banks of <hi>Savus,</hi> is his. In that perambulation is contained the greater part of <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary</hi> all <hi>Bosnia, Servia, Bulga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria, Macedon, Epire, Greece, Pelloponese, Thrace,</hi> and the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chipelago</hi> with the Islands. He hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in <hi>Asia</hi> and <hi>Africk,</hi> all that is between <hi>Velez de la Gomera</hi> and <hi>Alexandria</hi> in <hi>Aegypt,</hi> between <hi>Bugla</hi> and <hi>Guargula,</hi> between <hi>Alexandria</hi> and the City <hi>Siene;</hi> and from the City <hi>Suez</hi> as far as <hi>Swachen.</hi> The hugeness of this territory may be imagined by the circuit of some of the parcels: <hi>Palus Meotis</hi> (wholly his) spreadeth it self a thousand miles into the
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:208142:57"/> land; two thousand and seven hundred miles do hardly incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pass the <hi>Euxine</hi> Sea. The coast of the <hi>Mediterranean</hi> Sea (as much as is subject to him) contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in circuit eight thousand miles. <hi>Egypt</hi> wholly his, is esteemed three thousand and two hundred miles; so far from <hi>Der<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent</hi> upon the <hi>Caspian</hi> Sea to <hi>Aden</hi> upon the Red Sea; and from <hi>Balsara</hi> upon the <hi>Persian</hi> Gulf to <hi>Tremessen</hi> in <hi>Barbary,</hi> is accounted little less then four thousand miles. In the Sea, he is Lord of the most noble Islands of <hi>Ciprus, Eubea, Rhodes, Samos, Chio, Lesbos,</hi> and many other in the <hi>Archipelago,</hi> of which before.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:208142:57"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Tartaria Surveyed, with its Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>story.</head>
               <p>HAving thus surveyed the Turkish Dominions, it will be an acceptable endeavour I presume to give the Reader a little disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of the <hi>Tartar</hi> and his Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, which are linked and joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Religion and other com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacts to the Grand Seigniors, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause this Nation hath been as yet much unknown to us.</p>
               <p>TARTARIA is bounded on the East, with <hi>China,</hi> the <hi>Oriental</hi> Ocean, and the streights of <hi>Anian</hi> (if such streights there be) by which parted from <hi>America,</hi> on the West with <hi>Russia,</hi> and <hi>Podolia,</hi> a Province of the Realm of <hi>Poland;</hi> on the North with the main <hi>Scy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thick</hi> or <hi>Frozen</hi> Ocean; and on the South with part of <hi>China,</hi> from
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:208142:58"/> which separated by a mighty wall; the River <hi>Oxus</hi> parting it from <hi>Bactria</hi> and <hi>Margiana,</hi> two <hi>Persi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> Provinces; the <hi>Caspian</hi> Sea, which separates it from <hi>Media,</hi> and <hi>Hyrcania;</hi> the <hi>Caucasian</hi> moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains interposing betwixt it and <hi>Turcomania;</hi> and the <hi>Euxine,</hi> which divideth it from <hi>Anatolia</hi> and <hi>Thrace.</hi> So called from the <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars,</hi> a puissant and mighty people, now possessed hereof.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Tartaria</hi> briefly described.</label>It containeth all those great and spacious Provinces, which the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients called <hi>Seres, Scythia extra Imaum, Scythia intra Imaum, Saca, Sogdiana,</hi> the greatest part of <hi>Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matia Asiatica,</hi> and part of <hi>Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matia Europaea;</hi> extending it self the whole length of <hi>Asia,</hi> from the River <hi>Tanais,</hi> to the Eastern Ocean; taking in <hi>Taurica Cherso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesus,</hi> and some other parts of Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope also. So that if we measure it by miles, it is said to contain 5400 from East to West, and 3600 from North to South; a greater
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:208142:58"/> quantity of ground then the Turk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ish Empire, but of less fertility and account.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The smal<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> duration of the <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tars</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quests.</label> This extent in easier term<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> stret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched from the uttermost bounds of <hi>Asia</hi> to <hi>Armenia,</hi> and from <hi>Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gala</hi> to <hi>Volga,</hi> yea their incursions peirced even to <hi>Nilus</hi> and <hi>Danu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius.</hi> The <hi>Macedonian</hi> and Roman Empires were never so large. But because they were rather Runna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates then men of War, wanting politick Government and Military Discipline, sometime ruling one Province, sometime another, they rather wrought spoil and terror to the conquered Nat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ons, then fear of bondage and subjection, and at last seated themselves beyond the mountain <hi>Caucasus.</hi> After it became divided into many Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palities, yet so that the title and majesty of the Empire remained al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways to the great <hi>Cham,</hi> who took the original of this name from the great <hi>Chingis,</hi> the founder of this Empire.</p>
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:208142:59"/>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Tartari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and <hi>Crim Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar</hi> histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ified.</label> But leaving the great Cham of these <hi>Tartars,</hi> the Successors of <hi>Tamerlane,</hi> to remoter affairs, sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed by very learned men to be but an imaginary Titulado, and the shadow of the <hi>shadow of spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits,</hi> as they call their Emperor; our purpose obligeth us onely to an account of the <hi>Crim</hi> or <hi>Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copense Tartar,</hi> so called from <hi>Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copia,</hi> a cheif town thereof. This Tartary is bounded on the East with the River <hi>Danais,</hi> now <hi>Don,</hi> on the West with the River <hi>Nieper</hi> once called <hi>Borysthenes,</hi> by which it is parted from <hi>Podolia,</hi> on the North with part of <hi>Russia,</hi> and on the South with some part of the <hi>Euxine</hi> sea, by which lie the <hi>Circas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sians,</hi> a sort of warlike Christians, who sell their children to Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metans for to make Souldiers of them, such as were the Mamalukes, such now some of the Janizaries, and the Persian standing Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my.</p>
               <p>These Tartars are good Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:208142:59"/> for the most part (as their fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent irruptions into Europe do sadly manifest) especially at Bow and Arrows, which they use as dextrously as the <hi>Parthians;</hi> of late years they have been trained up to the Harquebuze, and the handling of a Scimetar. <label>Their Discipline of the <hi>Tartari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</hi>
                  </label> They are not to be vanquished but by death, as resolute against capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, the misery whereof they know from their own cruelties, yet at home are they more civil to Christians then abroad, for they have some honourable thoughts of our Saviour, more then other Mahometans, which hath invited many <hi>Greeks</hi> and <hi>Armenians</hi> to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habit with them.</p>
               <p>As to their modern History, and for what relates to our purpose, we must retrospect to the raign of Mahomet the first, the Turkish Emperour when they grew at last of so great power, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quering the <hi>Asiatick Tartars,</hi> which lay neerest to them, that
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:208142:60"/>
                  <hi>Mahomet</hi> the Great thought fit to keep them down before grown too strong for him:<label>The poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homet</hi> the great.</label> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore under colour of taking in the City of <hi>Capha,</hi> then possessed by the <hi>Genoese,</hi> made himself Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster of the greatest part of the <hi>Taurican Chersonese,</hi> and the port of <hi>Tanais;</hi> thereby commanding both <hi>Moeotis</hi> and the <hi>Euxine</hi> Sea.</p>
               <p>In the time of <hi>Selymus</hi> the first, who had Married the Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of this <hi>Crim-Tartar</hi> (for so they called him) and was aided by him with an Army of fifteen thousand men against his father; the Turks and these Tartarians grew into a League. The chief conditions of it were, that the Tartar should aid the Turk upon all occasions, with sixty thousand Horse, that they should not make war with any of their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, (except the <hi>Muscovite</hi>) without leave of the Turk; that they shall pay yearly to the Grand
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:208142:60"/> Signiour in the way of Tribute, three hundred Christians; that the new <hi>Cham,</hi> upon the death or deposition of his Predecessor, shall receive from the Great Turk a Royal Banner, in token of his Confirmation in that estate, that in reward of these services, the Crim Tartar shall have yearly from the Grand Seignior, five thousand five hundred Ducats, in the way of pension; and succeed finally in the Turkish Empire, if the male issue of the house of <hi>Ot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toman</hi> should chance to fail. <label>The con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dition be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tween the Turk an<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> the Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar in point of succession</label> Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording unto this agreement the Tartars have been aiding to the Turks from time to time, against the <hi>Persians, Polanders, Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, Moldavians,</hi> and indeed whom not; and that with great and puissant Armies, the Great <hi>Cham</hi> sometimes arming 150000. of his own Subjects (leaving but one man in an house to attend their Cattel;) and someti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding five thousand <hi>Circussians</hi> and
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:208142:61"/> others of the <hi>Asian Tartars.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>The Turks dealing with them.</label>Nothing so punctual is the Turk, on his part to perform the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract; who not content to have the Tartar for his friend, or at the worst his Homager, hath of late times attempted to make him his slave or vassal. For <hi>Amurath</hi> the third, quarrelling, <hi>Mahomet</hi> the <hi>Crim-Tartar</hi> for a design to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept <hi>Osman Bassa,</hi> in his way from <hi>Persia</hi> to <hi>Constantinople,</hi> authorized the same <hi>Osman</hi> to war upon him: by whom the poor <hi>Crim</hi> and his two Sons, betrayed by some of his own Councellors (corrupted with Turkish gold) were strangled with a Bowstring; <hi>Islan</hi> a brother of the <hi>Crims,</hi> first sworn a Vassal to the <hi>Turk,</hi> put into the place, and over him a <hi>Turkish Beglerbeg</hi> or <hi>Bassa,</hi> to command in cheif, What hopes he hath of succ eding in the <hi>Turkish</hi> Empire, if the house of <hi>Ot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toman</hi> should fail, hath been alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy taken into consideration, in
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:208142:61"/> our discourse upon that subject.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>His Reve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nue.</label>What the <hi>Revenue</hi> of this Prince is, it is hard to say: his subjects have little money, and live most upon the bartery of their Cattel. But besides what he hath in lands or Customes, and the 5500 <hi>Ducats</hi> yearly from the <hi>Turk,</hi> he hath the tenth of all the spoils which are got in the Wars, and a <hi>Checkine</hi> for ev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry captive, for some, two or three, (whosoever taketh them) accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto their estates.</p>
               <p>As for his powers what he can do in horse we have seen already; and as for foot, Ammunition, and other necessary, he is supplyed with them by the <hi>Turk,</hi> (who doth sometime espouse his quarrels;) by whose assistance they have brought the <hi>Moscovites</hi> to some ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremities.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:208142:62"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Of the Life and Imposture of Mahomet.</head>
               <p>LIttle reason hath the world to admire at the impiety of men how execrable soever, when it shall be fully informed of the most blasphemous designs of this vile and leud Deceiver, who by his prosperous and thriving delusions and abominations, hath given encouragement to succeeding and very modern times to practice and imitate his wicked example. Such a Miscellany of absurdities in mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and religious concernments could indeed hardly have been imagined to have found any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception among rational creatures; but such was the force of his bold Atheism, and his boasted familiari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with the Deity, and the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing insinuations of his sensual and material Paradise, how in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>congruously
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:208142:62"/> soever confounded in his Institutions, besides the fine novelty thereof to a Pagan peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that without very much ado this Impostor quickly planted his opinions so strong, that they have taken such root and spread so uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versally, that one whole half of the habitable world to this day ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heres to his doctrine.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Mahome<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> extracti<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </label>Most Writers accord that <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homet,</hi> which name in the <hi>Arabick</hi> signifies <hi>Indignation</hi> or <hi>Fury,</hi> was the son of <hi>Adalla</hi> a Merchant in <hi>Mecca,</hi> a City in <hi>Arabia Faelix</hi> but <hi>Jathrib</hi> an obscure Village there, is named for his extracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. His mother <hi>Hemina</hi> a Jew, and himself in <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 571. born <hi>Posthumus,</hi> though others say he was deprived of both his Parents at two years old, when a poor woman that laboured for her living bred him up, others say it was his Uncle; at sixteen years of age he became a Merchants Bondman, his name <hi>Abdalmutalif,</hi>
                  <pb n="112" facs="tcp:208142:63"/> his Master, pleased with his wit and dexterity, made him his Factor: He dead, <hi>Mahomet</hi> being then twenty five years old, married his Mistris, and until the thirty eighth year of his age he industri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously followed his trade of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize, avoiding no personal travel (as well in the Kingdoms of <hi>Egypt, Syria</hi> and <hi>Persia,</hi> as elsewhere) where profit might arise. Being then satisfied with wealth, and given to ease, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to think on higher things, whereof in his travels he had not been negligent, having been curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to understand the Religion of the Jews and Christians; which compared with the Idolatry wherein he was originally trained thirty years did work in him assurance that Paganism was the way of ignorance, but to whether of those to incline, he stood doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful. At last falling in company with two Christian Artificers in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants in <hi>Mecca,</hi> by conversa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:208142:63"/> with them (who read the Old and New Testament unto him, for himself was unlettered) he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred Christianism, and seemed of opinion that thereby onely a man might attain unto salvation, and accordingly he framed his life, which bred admiration in them that knew him, and gave him a greater reputation then he did expect.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>M homet</hi> aspire to the name of a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet.</label> But this hasty spring was quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly blasted; for the Devil, taking advantage by this his esteem, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed his heart with pride, which wrought in him a desire to be taken for a Prophet, thinking all other attributes of Religion and sanctity to be but vile and base: To aspire unto that opinion he embraced a solitary life, retyring to a Cave in the Mountains, where he lived free from the ordinary conversation of men; repaired seldom to his own home, and his speeches (mixt with gravity and holiness teaching good life, and beating down Idolatry) moved, not onely such as saw him
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:208142:64"/> to admire, but the rest also (that heard by other mens ears) held him to be a Saint. <label>
                     <hi>Mahomet</hi> troubled with the Falling sickness.</label> To increase this opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of sanctimony, of the falling sickness (wherewith he was afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) he made good use; for he gave it out (when he fell into his fits incident to that disease) that he conferred with the Angel <hi>Gabriel,</hi> by whom the pleasure of God was revealed unto him, and that his trance proceeded through the weakness of his earthly Carcase, that was astonished at the Divine presence of the Heavenly Ambas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sadour. To pass by the vulgar story of his pedigree.</p>
               <p>Grown now famous, he thought it necessary to divulge into the world some works in writing, whereby his name might encrease; His best help was a Jew Scribe, who for want of a better Scholar he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained; but shortly after, his Master the Devil (the Church of Christ then labouring with the sickness of many Heresies) pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:208142:64"/> the acquaintance of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian called <hi>Sergius</hi> born in <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria,</hi>
                  <label>The <hi>Monk S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rgius</hi> his Coadjutor</label> by profession a Monk, and by infection a Nestorian, witty, eloquent and learned, who (having mist of some Ecclesiastical prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which in his opinion he had deserved) full of despight and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, in a devillish discontent, (having fled out of <hi>Syria</hi> into the hous<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of <hi>Mahomets</hi> Master) sought as well to raise a scandal upon the Christian Religion, as upon the professors thereof, the readiest way to kindle this fire, he found to be <hi>Mahomet;</hi> who (as is already said) had won some ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary opinion of sanctity. After some conference between them, the Jew for insufficiency was discharged. <label>His dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice.</label>
                  <hi>Sergius</hi> being fully in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed how <hi>Mahomet</hi> had hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to proceeded, made him to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand how weakly and grosly he had erred in fundamental points necessary for the advancement of a new Religion; and cunningly
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:208142:65"/> shewed him, not only the means how to smooth his past errors without scandal, but to compose a new Treatise, collected out of the Old and New Testament, united into some common principles with devised additions of his own, to bring Christans, Jews, and Gentiles under one profession, that should give credit to his Doctrine, and humour the hearers which being divulged amongst the Idolatrous people (who were easily caught) spread the poyson it contained o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all the <hi>Arabies,</hi> but the wiser sort fearing (as they had cause) that the setling of a new Religion, might also draw with it a new form of Government; opposed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves against it, calling <hi>Mahomet</hi> an Imposter, reproving his hypocrisie, and taxing his sensuality and drunkenness (of both which he was guilty) and sent to apprehend him; whereof <hi>Mahomet</hi> from some of his friends in <hi>Mecca</hi> having notice left his Cave and fled to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarts,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:208142:65"/>
                  <hi>Sergius</hi> in the mean time sounding in the ears of the people his parts and piety (the sixteenth of <hi>July</hi> 622. <label>The <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyra.</hi>
                  </label> from which flight the Turks begin their computati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Hegyrathi</hi>) unto whom di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Novelists resorted; as also such as the Estates had banished for approving his late coyned trash: This swarm of Wasps be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing stirred, nothing but revenge could ease their hearts; <hi>Mahomet</hi> willingly taking the advantage there offered, enlarged his thoughts holding it now less difficil for him to gain a Kingdom, then the title of a Prophet, which he had ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained.</p>
               <p>To make a smooth way to his enterprize, by underhand means, he exaspered the heady Novelists (whereof there were many of wealth and estimation) to be sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible of their banishment, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair their wrongs by force; him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self r accounted unto them Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which assured him that God
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:208142:66"/> was displeased with the <hi>Meccans,</hi> for the rigorous prosecuting of him and his Sectaries; that God willed to chastise their Tyranny; of victory he was assured: and whosoever of them dyed in that Holy War, his soul should pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently ascend to Heaven: with these and such like motives,<label>Mahomet <hi>takes</hi> Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dina.</label> the giddy people encouraged and seduced, elected <hi>Mahomet</hi> to be their chief, who (ordayning Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers and Captains, and receiving an Oath of fidelity as well from them as from their troops) marched to the City of <hi>Medina,</hi> and though repulsed at first, (yet after a field fight with the said enemy, at a place called <hi>Bedez,</hi> often mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the <hi>Alcoron,</hi> where he had the Victory) took it by force, the cause of his quarrel being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended against the Jews Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue, which he converted into a Temple for his own abhominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: This first good fortune wrought the effect he desired, for
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:208142:66"/> instantly by his Army he was salu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Calipha; which interpreted, is King, and because his creation happened upon a Friday, that day was ordained by him to be their Sabboth.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Takes <hi>Mecca.</hi>
                  </label> His next conquest was the City of <hi>Mecca,</hi> where he triumphed in the blood of his Neighbour Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens, which was not spared; and proclaimed death to all those that did not embrace his Doctrine.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Opposed by the Nobles of <hi>Arabia.</hi>
                  </label> The Princes and great men in <hi>Arabia</hi> (opposite unto him) as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembled all their forces; <hi>Mahomet</hi> being too weak, was overthrown, wounded, and fled to <hi>Mecca;</hi> yet in the end (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he war continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) he prevailed, and reduced the three <hi>Arabies</hi> under his sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection. Grown great and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous with his Victories, (at that time the Emperor of <hi>Constan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople</hi> and King of <hi>Persia</hi> being men of weak and tame Spirits,) and assisted with the <hi>Saracens,</hi> who had been deceived and abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:208142:67"/> of their pay by <hi>Heraclius</hi> the Emperour, as also by <hi>Julian</hi> the Apostate, (f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r Mahomets appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance was signalized with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temporary raign of that miscre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant) <label>His con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quests.</label> he invaded their Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and with a conquering sword triumphed over <hi>Syria,</hi> the City of <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> the Kingdom of <hi>Meso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potamia</hi> and <hi>Persia,</hi> the great City of <hi>Babylon,</hi> with other Eastern Provinces; of all which, as of the <hi>Arabies,</hi> he stiled himself King. <label>And re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirement.</label> Being now grown elder by his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate life, in the state of his body then in years, which exceeded not sixty seven, full of glory, as well in regard of his large Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, as in opinion of sanctity, in being esteemed a Prophet, and weary with war, with a fained holiness, he retired to <hi>Mecca,</hi> the Metropolis of his new Empire (under which mask he intended to take his ease) sequestred him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self from publique affairs, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting the government of his
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:208142:67"/> estates to the Lieutenants, and within three years following, which was in <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 631. the sixtieth year of his Age, and the tenth of his reign he died; but others say in the seventieth of his age, and the twenty third of his impostures, and that he died frantick:<label>
                     <hi>Mahomet</hi> dies.</label> Upon his death-bed he commended unto his principal Commanders, the care and use of his fantastical Law, assuring them that it was agreeable to the Will of God, and that so long as they and their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterity should hold and maintain it, they should flourish. His dead body being kept four days in expectation of a resurrection, which he promised to perform in three, grown full of stench and putrefaction, was carried by his successors, who pretended to be his Caliphs or Vicar Generals, to <hi>Medina,</hi> where it yet continues, but not drawn up to the roof of the Chappel by a Load-stone, as is vulgarly fabled.</p>
               <pb n="122" facs="tcp:208142:68"/>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Mahomet</hi> pretends discent from <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham.</hi>
                  </label> This false Prophet and usurping Prince, pretended paternally to discend from the Patiarch <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> by his eldest Son <hi>Ismael,</hi> and to avoid the infamy of an unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful bed, he affirmed that <hi>Ismael</hi> was the Son of <hi>Sara,</hi> not of the Bondwoman <hi>Agar,</hi> whereupon the <hi>Arabians</hi> (which is the undoubted name of that people) are by some writers (of <hi>Ismael</hi>) called <hi>Isma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites,</hi> and by others (of <hi>Agar) Agarens;</hi> And (of <hi>Sara) Sara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens,</hi> but in this latter time they are distinguished by the name of <hi>Arabians, Moors,</hi> and <hi>Mahome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans,</hi> the first is proper onely to those which inhabit in <hi>Arabia:</hi> the <hi>Moors</hi> are the Progeny of such <hi>Arabians</hi> as after their Conquests seated themselvs in that part of <hi>Affrica:</hi> the <hi>Mahometans</hi> is the general name of all Nations that profess <hi>Mahomet,</hi> as <hi>Turks, Tartars, Persians,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Of the successors of <hi>Mahomet</hi> until the year of our Lord 673.
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:208142:68"/> the writers vary in opinion, both in name and number of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liphs, and in the years of their reigns: the reason that begat their errors proceeded from the dissen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that happened (about the succession) amongst <hi>Mahomets</hi> Kinsmen, evermore Anti-Caliphs starting up with pretended Titles in opposition to him that had the Diadem; whereof some were mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered and others deposed, so as the writers either out of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance (not able to discern the truth, or wilfully partial) have erred. Notwithstanding their civil tumults they kept <hi>Mahomets</hi> Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, and inherited his fortunes, for every of them added somwhat to his Monarchie, whereby they became fearful to the world, and potent in <hi>Asia, Affrica,</hi> and <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The fourth Caliph (agreed upon by Historiographers) was called <hi>Aozman</hi> or <hi>Azman,</hi> Husband to <hi>Mahomets</hi> Daughter, who per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:208142:69"/> (that in this upstart Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion) Schisms and diversities of opinions began to rise, by the help of his Wifes Mother recovered <hi>Mahomets</hi> papers wherein his Law was written, which with some additions of his own he caused to be digested into one volume, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining four books, divided into 124. Chapters, and called it the <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coran;</hi> that is to say, the <hi>Collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Precepts:</hi> the Original where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of they feign to be written in a Table which is kept in Heaven, and the Copy of it brought to <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met</hi> by the Angel <hi>Gabriel</hi> by his mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take, say the <hi>Persians,</hi> but for <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homets</hi> vertue, approved by God.<label>The e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steem of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choran.</label> A Book so highly reverenced by the <hi>Mahometans,</hi> that they write upon the Cover of it, <hi>let none touch this but he that is clean;</hi> Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding expresly upon pain of death, that that book, and that onely, should be received as <hi>Canonical,</hi> through his Dominions. The whole body of it is but an Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:208142:69"/> and gloss on these eight Commandements.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Every one ought to believe that God is a great God, and one onely God, and</hi> Mahomet <hi>is his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet.</hi>
                  <label>The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r opinion concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Christ.</label> They hold <hi>Abraham</hi> to be the <hi>Friend</hi> of God; <hi>Moses</hi> the <hi>Messenger</hi> of God; and <hi>Christ</hi> the <hi>Breath</hi> of God, whom they deny to be conceived by the <hi>Holy Ghost,</hi> affirming that the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> grew with Child of him by smelling to a Rose, and was delivered of him at her breasts. They deny the mystery of the Trinity, but punish such as speak against <hi>Christ;</hi> whose Religion was not (say they) taken away, but mended by <hi>Mahomet.</hi> And he who in his pilgrimage to <hi>Mecca,</hi> doth not comming or go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, visit the Sepulchre of <hi>Christ,</hi> is reputed not to have <hi>merited,</hi> or bettered himself any thing by his journey.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Every man must marry to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease the Sectaries of Mahomet.</hi> Four Wives he alloweth to every
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:208142:70"/> man, and as many Concubines as he will, between whom the Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band setteth no difference, either in affection or apparel, but that his Wives onely can enjoy his <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baths</hi> benevolence. The women are not admitted in the time of their lives to come into their Churches; nor after death to Paradise.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Every one must give of his wealth to the poor.</hi> Hence you shall have some buy slaves, and then manumit them; buy birds and then let them fly. They use com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly to free Prisoners, release Bond-slaves, build canes or lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in the ways for the relief of Passengers, repair bridges, and mend High-ways.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y one must make his prayers five times a day.</hi> When they pray they turn their bodies toward <hi>Mecca,</hi> but their faces sometimes one way, sometimes another way, beleiving that <hi>Mahomet</hi> shall come behind them, being at their devotions. And those which
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:208142:70"/> canno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> come, must when they hear the voice of the Cryars, fall down in the place where they are, do their devotions, and kiss the ground thrice.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Every man must keep a Lent one moneth in a year.</hi> This Lent is called <hi>Ramazan,</hi> in which they suppose the <hi>Alcoran</hi> was given unto <hi>Mahomet</hi> by the Angel <hi>Gabriel.</hi> This fast is onely intended in the day time, the law giving leave to frolick it in the night, as they best please, so they abstain from Wine and Swines flesh.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <label>
                     <hi>Turks</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural to their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents.</label>6. <hi>Be obedient to thy Parents.</hi> Which Law is the most neglected of any in all the <hi>Alcoran:</hi> never any children being so unnatural as the Turkish.</p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>Thou shalt not kill.</hi> And this they keep inviolated among themselves, but the poor Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians are sure to feel the smart of their fury. And as if by this law the actual shedding of blood onely were prohibited, they have inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:208142:71"/> punishments for their offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, worse then death it self.</p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>Do unto others, as thou woldst be done unto thy self.</hi>
                  <label>The <hi>Turks</hi> Paradise.</label> To those that keep these Laws he promiseth Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radise, a place of all delights, adorned with flowery fields, wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered with Chrystalline Rivers, beautified with trees of Gold; under whose cool shade they shall spend their time with amorous Virgins, whose mansion shall no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be far distant. The men shall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver exceed the age of thirty, nor the women of fifteen; and those to have their virginities renewed as fast as lost.</p>
               <p>He taught too, that at the end of the world, all men that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessed any such Religion, should go into <hi>Paradise;</hi> the <hi>Jews</hi> under the Banner of <hi>Moses;</hi> the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians</hi> under the Banner of <hi>Christ;</hi> and the <hi>Saracens</hi> under the Banner of <hi>Mahomet.</hi> They compel no man therefore to abjure the faith
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:208142:71"/> in which he was born, but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend and approve secretly such as they find zealous and constant in their own Religion; yet hold it an especial honour to have daily new <hi>Proselytes,</hi> they incite them by hope of freedom and preferment, which with many are motives too much prevailing.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Their absurd conceits of dooms<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>day</label> The opinions which they hold concerning the end of the world, are very ridiculous; as that at the winding of a horn, not all flesh onely, but the Angels themselves shall dye, that the earth with an Earthquake shall be kneeded to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether like a lump of Dough; that a second blast of the same horn shall after forty days restore all again; that <hi>Cain</hi> shall be Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain or Ring-leader of the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, who shall have the counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Dogs and swine; that they shall pass over the bridge of Justice, laden with their sins in satchels; that the great sinners shall fall into Hell, the lesser in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:208142:72"/> Purgatory onely; with a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand of the like fopperies, which it is needless to add here, conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that the <hi>Alcoran</hi> it self is now extant in English, and every one that lists may read it.</p>
               <p>I need not engage further in an account of his Doctrine, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended successors. But having shown you the Original and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of this Dominion, and how gained, and by what art enlarged into that bulk, and by force wrested from other Princes, (<hi>Mahomet</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending for his injurious invasions, the directions of God, who seeing his Law delivered by <hi>Moses</hi> and <hi>Christ</hi> to have been despised, because of the weak assertion thereof, would have them planted now by the Sword) we will next see by what means they are yet kept and maintained, and are like to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creased, namely by power, and the same militaty Maximes. <hi>Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um iisdem Artibus facile retinetur quibus acquiritur.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:208142:72"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Of their Militia.</head>
               <p>
                  <label>The In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fantry.</label> THeir Infantry consists of two sorts, First, such as are levyed upon particular Cities, more or less according to the nature of the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition, and proportionable to their abilities, from whence many Christians are frequently sent, both Turks and Christians well cloathed and armed, and exercised a moneth before they march without the Cities where they are raised: The second the <hi>Janizaries,</hi> who make 50000, which are Christian Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren taken from the Northern parts of <hi>Europe,</hi> and entred into the Grand Seigniors books, and bred in the Seraglio and other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as common servants till twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty two years old, and then are mustered and disciplined for ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:208142:73"/> (but now Turks are listed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them very frequently) these are the flower of the Army, and are never disbanded, but when old, are put into Garrison. <label>Their Cavalry.</label> The horse consist of the Spahioglans, whose just number is 32000, and are the constant guard of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors person at home and abroad; and the <hi>Timariots,</hi> who hold lands by serving the Sultan in his Wars, and according to the value of their Timarr or Farm sending three, four or six horses, but not all for service, their total number with the Tartar, whose aid of 60000 horse is always to be in a readiness may be 300000. of which number the Kingdom of <hi>Algeir</hi> affords 40000 that of <hi>Tunis</hi> 30000. <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poli</hi> 10000. we may not reckon proportionably, so with the other Provinces, because Horse are here in abundance.</p>
               <p>When a War is proclaimed, and a general Rendezvous appointed, the several Bassa's and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:208142:73"/> of Provinces draw their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces together, sommoning the Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mariots to do their service afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said, but many of them with some Janizaries and Voluntiers have leave to march before to the said Rendezvous.<label>The <hi>Tur<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> disciplin<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> in marc<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing.</label> When these Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shaws begin their march, publick proclamation is made to hang all such Janizaries as shall be found behinde those Forces upon their march; when they are rendezvou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, and upon the Expedition, the Bashaws do not go all in company, but setting forth about an hour one after another, draw out their Troops without confusion, not in any strict order of Rank and File, as near no enemy.</p>
               <p>Yet though there is not the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scipline of posture, their Officers commands are in all other things carefully obeyed; tis a wonder to see such a multitude, as common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they march with, so clear of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusion, violence, want, sickness or any other disorder, there being
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:208142:74"/> always plenty of good Bisket, Rice and Mutton carried with the Army.</p>
               <p>The Bashaws and great Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders have with them three or fourscore Camels, besides six or sevenscore Carts to carry the Bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage, and when the General takes horse, he hath five or six Coaches covered with cloath of Gold or rich Tapestry to carry his wives, some have with them twelve or sixteen, the least ten who when they enter the Coach, there are men placed on both sides holding up a row of Tapestry to cover them from being seen by the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, although they were mufled af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Turkish manner that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but their eyes appeared. <label>
                     <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>e <hi>Turks</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>domy.</label> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides these women, each Bashaw hath as many or rather more pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thick Boys which they use for So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domy, whom they prefer as the greater satisfaction before their Wives, which are used mostly to dress their meat, to wash, and
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:208142:74"/> for to honest their unnatural lust.</p>
               <p>The Boys are generally of four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen, ten or nine years old, and are usually clad in velvet or scarlet with gilt Scymetars, and bravely mounted with sumptuous furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to each of them a Souldier is appointed, who walks by his bridle for his safety.</p>
               <p>When the Prime Vizier departs upon any expedition out of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantinople,</hi> he wears in his Turbant a long broach Feather, which none but the Grand Signior usually wears besides himself, upon this onely occasion; He is accompanied on his way with all the Grandees of the Court, who present him with Gifts, as doth the Sultan him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self in vests and such like commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities, to bestow upon merit or other occasions for his Magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence. <label>Their Military musick.</label> The martial musick they have is none of the best, but will serve sufficiently to confound the senses, and deafen the ears to any
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:208142:75"/> other clamour, being a kind of hoarse Kettle Drum, which with some brass dishes and wind Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, carried by fellows on Horse-back, ride a little before every great Commander, and noyse along the journey. The great rendezvouz when he march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth against Christendom is always appointed in that fatal playn, of <hi>Thessaly</hi> famous for the battels of <hi>Pharsalia,</hi> between <hi>Pompey</hi> and <hi>Caesar,</hi> and <hi>Philippi</hi> between <hi>Augustus,</hi> and <hi>Cassius,</hi> and <hi>Brutus,</hi>
                  <label>
                     <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>heir <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>rms.</label> As for their armes which hath been touched before something more particularly is to be said of them. They differ from those of the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ropeans very much, yet their Harquebuze is something like our Caliver, their Scymetar a crooked flat backsword, good at Sea upon Boording, or among Ropes, but in field fight is much inferiour to the Rapier; but constant use (for it hath been always the Eastern weapon) gives them advantages,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:208142:75"/> more then we can ward.</p>
               <p>They use likewise an Iron Mace, either for stroke or hurle, and in this they have a peculiar excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, being brought up in it from their youth. <label>Bows and Arrows.</label> Bows and Arrows are no less skilfully then frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly used, with which they do most mischief, though the Arrows be no bigger then Childrens, but the strength of their Bows doth the Execution. Besides these they car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry other, almost all sorts of wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons with them, as they do the like when they travail, first their Girdle is charged with three or four pistols, then on either side a knife as long as a mans arm, like a skean but not so broad, with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother for ordinary uses, tuckt to his coat, a Harquebuze on his Shoulder, on his thigh a Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitar, on the one side of the Sad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle Pummel a Petronel, on the other a strange Sword, the blade being hollow and foursquare, by that either an Ax or an Hungarian
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:208142:76"/> Mace, or both, and at his back Bows and Arrows, so that he looks like a Porcupine, with weapons in every part of his body. The great ordinance each Souldier carries in his pocket in peices to the field or Leagure, where it is cast.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Their Quarters.</label> As to their Quarters, which are always in the fields and the open Ayr, but what their Tents some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times defend, all these arms are fastned to their Bridles, which are embellished with brass guilt bosses, and that is tied about the tree, or otherwise made sure to the ground, where he rests, that being cared for, he spreads a Blanket, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he first eats and then sleeps in his cloaths, with his Saddle for his Pillow; Armour they have not had long, but now they begin to use it frequently, the agility and celerity of men and horses in offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, equalling the defensive part. To 3. Horsemen a Wagon is allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to carry their other necessaries.</p>
               <p>When they approach an enemies
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:208142:76"/> Country, they march in Rank and file with wonderful exact order and silence, whereby commands are readily heard and obeyed; there being severe punishment for them that by disorderly and licencious behaviour, disturbe their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies. <label>Their provision on their march.</label> And for the bettter secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of this discipline, and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent stragling, they are always provided of Bisket, dry flesh, and store of rice, with a sort of course butter, so as in the greatest deso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late places and Countries, they have plenty of necessaries, which brings them in heart to the encounter.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Their Battel.</label> When they are neer an engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the horse (which is one of their chief Military politiques) encompass all their Infantry, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the Janizaries (whose cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and bravery they confide in) in the rear, in form of a half Moon or Crescent, which figure they esteem propitious. Those Horse have order not to meddle with the enemy, but onely to drive and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessitate
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:208142:77"/>
                  <label>Their manner of fighting.</label> the foot upon the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my till they have pierced through their Battaliaes if possible, and if they chance to recoyl, to hold them to the slaughter, till they have wearied and dulled the enemies Swords, and then the Janizaries and they together fall with fresh fury and vigour upon them, and this serves for all the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages of Military Policy and quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens his multitudes, through despe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, to high and gallant services.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Their Seiges and Leagures.</label> In matter of siege and Leagures, they are not altogether so expedite and understanding as the Europe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and what ever they have at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained to in matter of raising or ruining Fortifications, hath been taught them by Fugitives and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negadoes; the use of the Cannon they have learned very well, but yet it is not so familiar to them, for not many Matrosses are to be found in their Country, the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sian</hi> their next neighbour to this day standing six or eight yards off
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:208142:77"/> when he gives fire to those pieces.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Their bold ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches.</label> Their number serves them for shelter and defence, for as soon as they have raised a battery, and made a kind of brest work, with some Mounts in it to overlook the place besieged, they make their approaches in spight of the bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let, and strive to fill up the Trenches with their bodies, if they cannot do it with other matter, and when once a breach is made, is is either a Souldiers death there in honour, or a Dogs in the Camp for an Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer to retreat, or give over the assault while Commanded.</p>
               <p>Yet they can use Galleries, as they do mines and other devices of conquest, but neither with that art or success as the Christians, but that is equalled with their dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence and undefatigable work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and obstinate resolution of carrying the Town at last. And their patient suffering of all extremities upon such a bent is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most incredible, and the like they
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:208142:78"/> do in defence of their own.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The <hi>Turk</hi> always Master of the field.</label> But the Turk puts not himself to much charge of Garrisons, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less Frontiers and maritime Towns, (which are not yet so strictly guarded and maintained as with us) for he supposeth himself Master of the field, and that up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any sudden rupture he is able to march with a sufficient Army to their relief (the places being provided for such a competent time) besides, after the conquest of a Country, he divides it as was partly said before, into so many Timars or Farms, for which the several possessors are bound always to be in a readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, with two, three or six horses according to the value of the said lands, who do so awe the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, (the Nobility and better sort being either transplanted and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroyed, and some Rusticks onely left to till &amp; manure the ground,) that seldom happens any revolt meerly by them, the <hi>Morlacks</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted,
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:208142:78"/> whose poverty suited not with their Lordly Greatness, nor was able to maintain it among so many natural wants and indigen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Their Naval force.</label> As to their Naval force it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sists of three Fleets, the one (like our <hi>Newcastle</hi> Traders) sails the <hi>Euxine</hi> and <hi>Mediterranean</hi> seas, either toward the <hi>Moscovite, Circasse</hi> or <hi>Cossack,</hi> and thence bringing slaves, with honey, wood and wax, &amp;c. returns to <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantinople</hi> about <hi>August,</hi> and thence sails to <hi>Alexandria</hi> to bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter those commodities for Flax, Sugar, Tapestry, Sherbets (made of several dry preserved fruits, as Apricocks, Peaches, Citrons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) Corn, Rice and other Egyptian traffick, and returns with Tribute (guarded with a Fleet for fear of the <hi>Malta</hi> and <hi>Florentine</hi> Galleys which lye in weight for the strag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers) in <hi>January</hi> back to <hi>Constan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Of late for fear of the said Galleys, it comes by Land in Caravans.</note> which is as the Nursery of his Seamen. The second is his fleet
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:208142:79"/> of War, built and equipped in the Streights, and made only for fight. The third, the Barbary men of War, which exercise Piracy o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all Christendom.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rats of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers,</hi> &amp;c.</label> This last is his cheifest strength, though not so much and so soon at command as the other; for they have long pretended an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependance on the Grand Seigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or, when appealed to from those they have robbed, which he like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise dissembles, so that sometimes they prefer their own designs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his quarrel; but generally they comply with his Orders.</p>
               <p>Notwithstanding to give the world to believe that they are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt from the Turkish jurisdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and to be reputed free Pirats, for fear of restoring their prizes, they will not come to Anchor un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the reach of any of the Forts or Castles belonging to the grand Signior, but if they have occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to stay for a wind or other convenience, ride at anchor for a
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:208142:79"/> while out of danger of any shot; which personates the exemption very finely.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The <hi>Turk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ish</hi> store of Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</label> They are notwithstanding ill supplied with Seamen, for besides Renegadoes they have very few skilful Saylors; these Renegadoes in the Barbary Fleet have taught them to sail into the North-wester<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most parts of <hi>Europe,</hi> they having sometimes landed in <hi>Cornwal</hi> by night, and carried away some cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives out of their Beds; they have frequently infested <hi>Spain</hi> in the same manner, and now they have proceeded so far that they roave as far as <hi>Newfoundland,</hi> and have taken prizes there, and in one of the Ships a very handsome English woman going for <hi>Virginia,</hi> who was presented by the Captain to the Grand Seignior and is by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port at present in his Seraglia, and one of the Sultanaes.</p>
               <p>The Seamen are generally very civil and courteous, as they are obedient and diligent, and not ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>religious
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:208142:80"/> and prophane, as too many of our Mariners are, and rough and quarrelsome besid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, their Terms of Navigation are altogether <hi>Italian,</hi> from whose commerce they borrowed it, them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves having formerly few or no Ports to the Sea.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Their ves<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sels.</label> Their own Ships called Caramu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zaels are most part great Ships, with Poop and Fore-castle very high, and will carry seven or eight hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred passengers, but like Portugal Galleons are slow of sayl, not fit for service in fight, and are soon overset by any sudden tempest, or stormy weather. <label>
                     <hi>Holland</hi> prizes.</label>The best Ships therefore they have are such as they have taken from the <hi>Hollander,</hi> who to save their lives and liberty, which the Turks promise upon a present surrender, will part with their Ships and Goods, which turns to the unspeakable prejudice of other Christians trading in the Levant, especially the <hi>Venetians,</hi> who have often times encountred the Turks
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:208142:80"/> at Sea within these few years.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>An Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploit.</label> This makes the Pyrats of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giers, Salley,</hi> and <hi>Tripoli</hi> to have such a contemptuous opinion of that Nation, and always apt to flinch from such terms of peace as are every foot agreed on between them; but with us they care not how little they quarrel, for that they seldome get any thing by the bargain, but frequently come by the worst, a single Merchant man having spoyled two of their best men of war, and slain almost all their men, with their Captain Bashaw of <hi>Rhodes,</hi> about which a great difference was like to have arisen in the year 1634. by a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint made against the English at the Port.</p>
               <p>It were to be wished therefore that the Turk were no more formi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable at Land then he is like to be at Sea, of which the <hi>Venetians</hi> have continued Masters, and by their annual espousal have wedded it to their Fortune and Glory,
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:208142:81"/> which hath in several triumphs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorned that mayden and little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publique, against the huge and bulky mightiness of this Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The <hi>Turk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ish</hi> Arse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals for shipping.</label> The Turkish Arsenals for ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping are four; the first is at <hi>Pera,</hi> and contained thirty three docks or mansions for so many Gallies: The second is at <hi>Callipolis,</hi> and contained twenty, both under the charge of the high Admiral and his Servitors: The third, is at <hi>Suez</hi> upon the red Sea, containing twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty five mansions, and the fourth and last, at <hi>Balsaro</hi> in the Persian Gulfe, consisting of fifteen Gallies, and these two last under the charges of the <hi>Beglerbegs</hi> of <hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saro</hi> and <hi>Cairo;</hi> but of late years there are double the number built at <hi>Pera</hi> and in <hi>Callipolis.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="149" facs="tcp:208142:81"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Of their Government Civil and Ecclesiastick.</head>
               <p>THE Court is commonly stiled by them <hi>Capy,</hi> viz. the port, wherein are many great Officers, partly spoken of before, and whose services are onely destinated to uses within the <hi>Seraglio</hi> (too large to be here described further then what was mentioned in the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scription of <hi>Constantinople;</hi>) and they are for the most part Eunuchs, with their table of under Eunuchs. But without the Seraglio are also diverse honourable offices for the Government of the Empire, the chief whereof is their Mufti or Pope, who onely hath plenary power to interpret their Law and Alcoran. In the second Rank, are their <hi>Caldeleschers,</hi> viz. Chief Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stices, and they have the hearing and deciding of all temporal suits
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:208142:82"/> between party and party. <label>The great Officers of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire.</label> In An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient times they were but two, one in <hi>Rum Ili</hi> or Europe, the other in <hi>Natolia:</hi> but <hi>Selimus</hi> the third, added a third equal in authority to the other two, over the Provinces of <hi>Egypt, Syria, Arabia,</hi> and part of <hi>Armenia.</hi> These chief Judges have jurisdiction over all inferior Justices, or Caddies in particular Provinces, and by them are nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated, but confirmed by the Grand Seignior himself. After the <hi>Cadeleschers,</hi> followeth the Viceroy <hi>Bassaes</hi> (counsellours of estate) whose number is uncertain; in old time three or four, but of late twelve. The President of these the Turks term Vizeroy Azem, and in truth, is a personage of great dignity, and authority in mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the affairs of the State, as the man with whom the Grand Seignior doth onely communicate his weightiest intentions, and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretest deliberations.</p>
               <p>In the next place appear the <hi>Beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerbegs</hi>
                  <pb n="151" facs="tcp:208142:82"/> (masters <hi>del Campo</hi>) <label>Major Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals.</label> the chief whereof is he that is tear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of <hi>Romania</hi> or <hi>Grecia:</hi> The second is the Beglerbeg of <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talia</hi> or <hi>Asia.</hi> The third is the <hi>Denizi</hi> Beglerbeg, that is to say, the Lord high Admiral. And these three Beglerbegs have equal place and authority with the former Bassaes in the <hi>Divano,</hi> or place of publique audience.</p>
               <p>Before the last war of <hi>Persia,</hi> this Empire was under-Governed by forty Beglerbegs, who like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise had under them two hundred and seventy Sanjacks (but since those times this number, hath been much augmented) <hi>viz.</hi> in Europe resided seven, in Affrick four, in Asia 29.</p>
               <p>His yearly revenue, without coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his Timars, by them he hath 30000 horse always in pay (which are farms held as by Knights ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and remove the wonder his Revenue is so little) is estimated at fifteen Millions of Duckats.</p>
               <pb n="152" facs="tcp:208142:83"/>
               <p>
                  <label>The Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>van.</label> As to the Capy or Port, by which is insinuated the safety and Harbour of such as address them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves to the Grand Signior, the remarkable thing besides the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors places of pleasure which are hinted in the other part is the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>van</hi> or places of Judicature, where the Visiers, and the two Cadiles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers sit four days in every week. <label>A nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble story of Sultan <hi>Morat.</hi>
                  </label> Their decisions are speedy and most just, for that the Grand Seigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or hath a place private to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self to inspect their Deportment; and it is very certain that the late Sultan <hi>Morat</hi> being there one day, and hearing judgement given a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst a Coyner, to lose his right hand, which is the onely punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for that fact, by a waft of his hand out of the window, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seen to any but the Executioner, gave a sign for cutting of the Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows Head, as judging him to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve death, which the Executio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner performing, to the amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the <hi>Divan,</hi> they sentenced
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:208142:83"/> him to the same infliction (for sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence and Execution are done at one and the same time) which the fellow preparing for, and refusing to give any account or reason of his Action, as relying upon the Emperors intervention, was by his own mouth, out of the same Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacy absolved and acquitted of the fact, as done by his Command.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours publick appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance eve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry Friday <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>revents In<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tice.</label> Besides, by the Emperors publick appearance every Friday, when he goes in great State on Horse-back to the Temple of St. <hi>Sophia,</hi> attended by no less then 20000. men, such is the Majesty, and consequently the awful dread of this Prince (though to their joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful acclamations he will answer by bestowing his blessings chearfully upon the people, and shows him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self ready to receive all manner of complaints from all manner of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, insomuch that none of his attendants dare deny the receipt of any paper from the meanest wretch, nor the greatest of his
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:208142:84"/> Officers hope for any favour upon any true information of their op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression and injustice) I say by this means justice is kept most part uncorrupted, and the Grand Seignior upon the account of his impartial severity towards his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters, though he squezeth to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self by their death or exile the juyce of their oppression, is most infinitely beloved and admired by his sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, being by his state, magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, and justice, conceived by them to have something more then humane in his nature.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The <hi>Turks</hi> Trials.</label>As to their common Trials, (which is by way of <hi>viva voce,</hi> and the Oaths of Witnesses) though of late the attestation of a Musselman or Turkish beleiver is often taken for an authentick proof against a Stranger, yet in their ordinary trials between one another, they do proceed with more caution, and upon surer grounds, (for even the Religious orders of which there are four,
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:208142:84"/> and are presumed for the honour of their Religion not to be tainti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble with any crime are given most excessively to subornation and perjury) extracting ground and just presumptions for sentence from private examinations and questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, so artificially put, as no pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meditated combination can evade, <label>Turks re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>verence Oaths more the Christian</label> yet generally the Turk bears a more awful reverence to Oaths then Christians, nor are they found to alloy it with the poyso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous mixtures of equivocation, though the Jews that live among them are very prone to forswear and abuse that sacred name they pretend to have in so much vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and for this reason and other wicked subtilties of that people, they will not suffer them to turn Turks, (which they would readily do, because of the same common principle of Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion) unless they will first turn Christians, which goes against the grain, and keeps numbers of them
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:208142:85"/> from being converts to <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>The Muf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti.</label> But to proceed, from all Judges both extrordinary and ordinary at the Port, and in the several Villages of the Provinces (for a Justice or Caddie is appointed for every Town) there lies an appeal to the Mufti or Muhumetan chief Bishop (who is next to be consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered in the Government) to whom all controversies difficulties or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted judgment are submitted for his final sentence, and even the grand Seignior himself doth and must refer himself, but his Oracle is sounded before, and must not utter one word more or less then is directed to him, and shall fit the convenience of State, for as it hath been excellently observed, the Turk hath the Mufti and Mecca both in his own Dominions, and is not forced in some untoward occurrences to apply himself to forrain dispensations. And some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the Grand Signior makes
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:208142:85"/> not nice to remove this Arch-Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyman, as well as other of his Tribe, if they once interfere with the State, yet without any tumult or Faction, or scarce any blemish to the persons of the men, who shall be reputed Saints, and so Calendaried, even if put to death, such is the radical opinion of their unstained sanctity and inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity.</p>
               <p>As to the Bashaws and Begler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>begs, and their honours for life, their posterity being reckoned for no more then common Turks, unless their own worth shall raise them, by which all potent combination of families is preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, having spoken something more liberally of it in the former Part, we must omit it here.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The nu<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber of h<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> Christia<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> Vassals.</label> In the time of <hi>Selimus,</hi> were reckoned one million and thirty three thousand Christian souls to live within his Dominions, not accounting those that enjoyed freedom of conscience by privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:208142:86"/> nor those that then were subject to the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Sultan, whom the said <hi>Selimus</hi> vanquish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but now they are in far greater numbers.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>f Jews <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ewise.</label> The Jews likewise live disper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed over his whole Dominions, in such infinite numbers, that scarce no town nor Village, but is very populously replenished with their Families, speaking diverse Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages, and using the trade of Marchandize in ample and rich fashion. Thus to my power have I laid out the portraiture of this mighty, tyranical, irreligious and bloudy Empire, which as it began by the sword, and is propagated by the sword, so let all Christians henceforth pray, that by the sword it may fall, and at last vanish into nothing, as of nothing (to speak of) it took Originall.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="159" facs="tcp:208142:86"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> The Continuation of the <hi>Turks</hi> Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>story.</head>
               <p>
                  <label>The Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siers de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign on <hi>Presburg</hi>
                  </label>
                  <hi>NEwhausel</hi> being reduced, which was supposed, and vainly hoped, would have disap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed the Turks Progress, and success for this year, being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined so far as the depth of win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the Grand Visier undertook some farther conquest, and with his Army, leaving a sufficient Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rison, and other numbers to repair and better fortifie the Fort, by bringing the River <hi>Niutre</hi> round about it, marched towards <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg,</hi> the Capital City or Metro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polis of lower <hi>Hungary,</hi> and with his approach gave out rumours of his resolution to attaque it, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lying on his first fortune, and
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:208142:87"/> those popular insinuations he had spread abroad of his reality, justice and tenderness to such pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as should come in to his Masters protection, with which thriving artifice he had already gained up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the credulity of most of the Pesants and indefensible places.</p>
               <p>Besides the honour of the place, as the repository of the Crown of <hi>Hungary</hi> (which the Hungarians most religiously reverence, as placing the safety and glory of their Nation therein, and which being seized, would have intituled the winner and wearer to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom) the convenience thereof as freeing his way to <hi>Vienna,</hi> on one part; and to <hi>Commorra, Raab,</hi> or <hi>Newhausel</hi> on the other, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarily incomodating any attempt upon the Island of <hi>Schut,</hi> by its Neighbourly correspondence and assistance in case of danger, where at present the General Count <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rini</hi> was enquartered, was a great motive and incitement to an at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:208142:87"/> against it. <label>Contents himself with sub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mission o<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> places a<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>jacent.</label> But such had been the vigilance and care of Count <hi>Strozzi</hi> a famous and experienced Souldier, in providing and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishing the City, wherein the hope of the Kingdom was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, and his courage, and all other excellent qualities of a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour, so known and beleived by this discreet Vizier, that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenting himself with the submission of <hi>Modern,</hi> St. <hi>George, Posing</hi> and other places that lay open and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed to his power, and the bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very and gallant designment of so high an enterprise, which the unim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peded conduct of the affair, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated honorably: and as if he had proceeded so far meerly upon a plot and design to surprize some places by his sudden return, he presently invested <hi>Niutra,</hi> a place neer <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hausel,</hi> and as well fortified, and more respected, because of its Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiastical concernment, as being a Bishops see, and by terrifying menaces and preparations for a
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:208142:88"/> storm, soon wrought upon the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendants to a surrender, who by the Articles thereof were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed to <hi>Presburg.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Nuntia</hi> yeilded.</label> The speedy and lucky event of this rendition, was effectual to his practices upon other places, for upon the same score <hi>Tyrnaw</hi> and some other Towns thereabouts opened their Gates and submitted to him, upon his common Terms of Religion and Liberty, <label>Bafled <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>Schinta.</hi>
                  </label> which success invited him to the Siege of <hi>Schinta,</hi> a very strong and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderable Fortress, and a Magazine of a great and the best quantity of the Emperors Artillery, but by the fidelity and valour of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour and his men, was repulsed thence, and glad to abandon the enterprize, for that <hi>October</hi> was more then half spent, and the climate did much incommodate his <hi>Asian</hi> and <hi>African</hi> Souldiery.</p>
               <p>Therefore to provide them of warmer Winter Quarters, to keep them well and in health against
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:208142:88"/> the Spring, <label>Retires t<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> Winter quarters</label> he repassed his great Guns with some of his Army over his Ship bridge to <hi>Gran</hi> or <hi>Strigoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> rumouring that when he had disposed of those unuseful peices in the depth of winter, he would return himself with his Europeans and prosecute the War, but in fine, he passed over his whole Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, being followed in his rear, in expectation of advantage by General <hi>Serini,</hi> who having par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with General <hi>Montecuculi,</hi> (conjoyned in attendance of the <hi>Newhausel</hi> design upon the Island of <hi>Schut</hi>) did at last cut off some 600. Janizaries with 200. other <hi>Besonio's,</hi> or Baggage people, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in the defence thereof, which they resolutely maintained, by barricadoing themselves among the Wagons, so that <hi>Serini's</hi> Hussars were forced to alight and follow them a foot into their advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and there couragiously slew them; (This was some expiation of that defeat given to Count <hi>Forgatz</hi>
                  <pb n="164" facs="tcp:208142:89"/> very neer the same place) as a fortnight before his brother and he had defeated two great parties, but not with so great success. This hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened about the last of <hi>October,</hi> and so those parts of this side the <hi>Danow,</hi> conceived some joyful hopes of a respit till the coming of the Spring.</p>
               <p>But the Vizier by those other after accessions had so strongly fixt himself, by leaving a Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of 4000. men in <hi>Newhausel,</hi> and 1500 in <hi>Niutre,</hi> besides a body of 10000. men to be ready to assist them upon all occasions, that the Christians are still kept to their Arms to attend their motion, and guard themselves. <label>
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>paffis</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>igue <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ith the <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>urk dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>vered.</label> And to increase the danger, <hi>Apaffi</hi> the Prince of <hi>Transilvania,</hi> whom they looked upon as under a constraint of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance with the Turks, and a se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret well-wisher to the Christian cause, discovered himself a decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and profest enemy, being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veagled with an investiture of
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:208142:89"/> those places taken this <hi>Campagnia,</hi> and upon the total Conquest, with the Crown of <hi>Hungary:</hi> for as soon as they were rid of the Infidels, he with his half Christians, <hi>Valachi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Moldavians,</hi> intermixed with <hi>Tartars,</hi> and his own plundering <hi>Transilvanians,</hi> undertook the Lieutenant-ship of the Winter War, those Nations being better able, as inured to the climate, to undergo the extremities of the weather.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Apaffi</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nages the Winter war.</label>
                  <hi>Apaffi's</hi> first design was upon the <hi>Berg</hi> Towns, or Mine Hills, whence the Hungarian Gold is fought, which as soon as he had parted with the Grand Visier, then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treating to <hi>Belgrade,</hi> he attempted, and this the easier, for that there was no resistance in readiness to oppose him, the forces that were raised by the Counts of <hi>Cochary</hi> and <hi>Tekelly</hi> in the upper <hi>Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> for the most part (for that the lower was already joyned with <hi>Serini,</hi> or awed by the Turks)
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:208142:90"/> were a little before, (maugre the enemies design of impeding them) already arrived to the gross of the Army; which also for want of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessaries for Man and Horse, and voured by the Turks as now dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>persed into Quarters.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>is design <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>pon the <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ine <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>owns.</label>The two first obstacles of his design upon the Mine Towns, and which barred his entrance, were the two Towns of <hi>Levents</hi> and <hi>Novigrad,</hi> reputed one of the prime places of upper <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary; <label>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>ventz</hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ilded.</label> Levents</hi> was also well ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, having in it a Castle manned with couragious Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and firmed with thick walls, flankers and Turrets, that accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly gave the enemy a rude and unwelcom entertainment, but their numbers being not to be wearied and no relief to be expected by the besieged, it was yeilded by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement, and the Articles ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the modern policy of the Turks punctually observed.</p>
               <p>From thence <hi>Apaffi</hi> marched to
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:208142:90"/>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Novigrad</hi> lately yeil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</label>
                  <hi>Novigrad,</hi> lying further in upper <hi>Hungary,</hi> which after a stout but short resistance, not without sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picion that the Governour was of <hi>Apaffi's</hi> party (more obvious now by his retreat into the Enemies Country, and the neutrality or rather assistance of the whole Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, as to the generality, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Apaffi</hi>) was rendred like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, and the Garrison dismist, but not into Christian quarters, being set to work, and enjoyned to be in readiness to assist their late Besiegers.</p>
               <p>The enemy encroaching thus up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Mine Towns, some Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which could be best got to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether were sent to enforce them, and to hinder them from setling their Winter quarters in those places, which were nevertheless much despaired of, for that <hi>Apaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fi</hi> with his aids threatned <hi>Cassovia</hi> the Metropolis of upper <hi>Hungary</hi> with a present siege, as he did in effect beleagure <hi>Fillek,</hi> some ten
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:208142:91"/> miles distant, prejudging that the Christians, if once able to take the field, would carry the War into these Quarters, of which therefore they would betimes possess them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves,<label>Seizeth some of the Mine Towns.</label> and therefore notwithstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the prevention aforesaid, they soon after seised on <hi>Shomnitz, Cremnitz</hi> and other Towns of the Mines; and by threatning Letters and summons terrified the people thereabouts to an acquiescence and submission under their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand: They faced likewise <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kay</hi> (the strongst Hold of all) with parties; but neither their courage, multitudes, practices or hopes, served them to the adventure of a siege.</p>
               <p>Nevertheless to countenance such resolutions, they spread ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours abroad as if the <hi>Grand Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sier</hi> would presently return, and orders were indeed to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose dispatcht to the Magistrates of <hi>Frystad</hi> to make ready two Bridges over the <hi>Waegh,</hi> so broad
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:208142:91"/> as that whole Squadrons might pass over there a breast, another irruption into <hi>Moravia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Count <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henlo</hi> Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral of the Aux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iliaries.</label> This news caused Count <hi>Serini,</hi> who till then continued in the Isle of <hi>Schut,</hi> observing the designs of them at <hi>Newhausel,</hi> to put him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self into motion, which presen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him with some considerable booties, (but inconsiderable par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,) designed for <hi>Constantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple;</hi> and that was all he was able to do; the Auxiliaries of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire amounting in all not to above 8000. men under command of the Count of <hi>Hohenlo,</hi> (whose An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cestors were famous in the low Country war) by their surfeits upon the fruits of the Country, which are in great abundance in the Hereditary Dominions, being so diseased that they were in no condition or capacity for any field service; to increase these Auxili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aries the Sweeds were neer upon their arrival from <hi>Bremen,</hi> with 700. Horse well mounted, but
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:208142:92"/> now like to have met with some danger at <hi>Erford,</hi> as the <hi>Hessen Darmstad Ayds</hi> perished with a greater misfortune upon the <hi>Danu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius</hi> in their passage to <hi>Vienna.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>The Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or to <hi>Regens<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh</hi> or <hi>Ratisbone.</hi>
                  </label> Neither were the Frontive Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risons better conditioned by want of many necessaries, even <hi>Raab</hi> and <hi>Comorra,</hi> where the Officers that surrendred <hi>Newhausel</hi> had been newly acquitted, so that amidst so many exigencies and streights every thing was feared to excess; The Emperor himself was at this time departing from <hi>Vienna</hi> to the <hi>Diet</hi> he had summoned at <hi>Regens<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pu g,</hi> to consider with the Princes of <hi>Germany</hi> of some quick expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to redress those evils, leaving the Archduke <hi>Charls Joseph</hi> to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern in his absence, who to add affliction to misery is since deceased, (as our latest intelligence) and the direct line of the imperial Family totally extinguished, a matter of no small moment to some designs in the world, especially since the
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:208142:92"/> Pope and the French are now so neer a rupture, yet to alleviate the present distress, providence was pleased to bestow on the vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance and conduct of Count <hi>Seri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni,</hi> a very remarkable success. <label>Count <hi>S<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rini</hi> give a great defeat to the Turk</label> The Forces of <hi>Apaffi</hi> intermingled with <hi>Tartars,</hi> and some <hi>Turks,</hi> pursuing their design of another invasion into <hi>Moravia;</hi> having also an eye upon the Island of <hi>Schut,</hi> had pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately laid a Bridge over the River <hi>Mur,</hi> and had passed two thousand Horse already over it; of which <hi>Serini</hi> having good and timely no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice by a discharge of a Cannon, he rise from his post, and with his Troops so fiercely charged them, that betwixt surprised and dismayed, and fairly worsted, they betook themselves back to the Bridge, where rancountring with numbers of their fellows passing over in great hast to them, they could neither go forward nor backward, but were forced to take the River, which spared none, there
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:208142:93"/> escaped very few of those 2000. this was done in the morning, <hi>Novemb.</hi> 27. when <hi>Serini</hi> brought two field peices and 300. of his Foot to face the Enemy, who stood on the other side the water and managed a revengeful Skirmish all the day long, and then retreated towards <hi>Canisia,</hi> from whence they are dreaded to reinforce this their first attempt, being excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly inraged at this disgraceful disappointment.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ffairs of <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>he Diet.</label> There is mention made in the <hi>Diet,</hi> of Mars. <hi>Turenne</hi> to succeed in the supreme command in <hi>Hungary,</hi> by means of an invitation, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest to the French King; but what the result of that and other things that concern this Subject to be consulted in that Grand Assembly may prove, we must refer to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther continuation if God permit.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="postscript">
               <pb facs="tcp:208142:93"/>
               <p>
                  <add>JƲst now is arrived a cetain re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, out of <hi>Transyvania</hi> and <hi>Valachia,</hi> That there is a very great feud and rupture happened between the Turks and Tartars, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> the grounds of it uncertainly deliverd<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> Some are of opinion, that the Turk, quartering so near him this winter, and seeing him partly engaged with the <hi>Pole</hi> (which he pretends to stomack) and partly imbodied with himself, designed a surpri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>al of this Empire, and to unite the whole force thereof with his own, which the Reader may be induced to believe from a former precedent mentioned in this Treatise: others affirn that the Tartar disappointed of his pay, and having endured all the miseries of the Campagnie, abridged likewise of the best part of his spoils, did revengefully and in great indignation begin the quarrel. However it was caused, most certainly such a different is risen among them, that much blood</add>
                  <pb facs="tcp:208142:94"/>
                  <add>hath been liberally spent between them, no les then a 1000 Janizaries at one time with their supplements far greater in number having been cut off in an encounter by the Tartars, and a very far invasion made into the Turks Country, with fire and sword.</add>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <add>Not to mention other troubles in <hi>Asia,</hi> which may by the blesing of God and his pity of distracted Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stendom, give this insolent Enemy a timely diversion.</add>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>
               <add>
                  <hi>FINIS.</hi>
               </add>
            </trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:208142:94"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>